<!-- TopBraid BaseURI: http://fundontology.com/fr/CFR-2012-title17-vol3-part275 -->
<CFRGRANULE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="CFRMergedXML.xsd">
    <FDSYS>
        <CFRTITLE>17</CFRTITLE>
        <CFRTITLETEXT>Commodity and Securities Exchanges</CFRTITLETEXT>
        <VOL>3</VOL>
        <DATE>2012-04-01</DATE>
        <ORIGINALDATE>2012-04-01</ORIGINALDATE>
        <COVERONLY>false</COVERONLY>
        <TITLE>RULES AND REGULATIONS, INVESTMENT ADVISERS ACT OF 1940</TITLE>
        <GRANULENUM>275</GRANULENUM>
        <HEADING>PART 275</HEADING>
        <ANCESTORS>
            <PARENT HEADING="Title 17" SEQ="1">Commodity and Securities Exchanges</PARENT>
            <PARENT HEADING="CHAPTER II" SEQ="0">SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE COMMISSION (CONTINUED)</PARENT>
        </ANCESTORS>
    </FDSYS>
    <PART>
        <EAR>Pt. 275</EAR>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 275—RULES AND REGULATIONS, INVESTMENT ADVISERS ACT OF 1940</HD>
        <CONTENTS>
            <SECHD>Sec.</SECHD>
            <SECTNO>275.0-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>General procedures for serving non-residents.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.0-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>References to rules and regulations.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.0-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>General requirements of papers and applications.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.0-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Procedure with respect to applications and other matters.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.0-6</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Incorporation by reference in applications.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.0-7</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Small entities under the Investment Advisers Act for purposes of the Regulatory Flexibility Act.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.202(a)(1)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Certain transactions not deemed assignments.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.202(a)(11)(G)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Family offices.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.202(a)(30)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>
                <PRTPAGE P="936"/>Foreign private advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Application for investment adviser registration.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Withdrawal from investment adviser registration.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Hardship exemptions.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203(l)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Venture capital fund defined.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203(m)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Private fund adviser exemption.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Eligibility for SEC registration; switching to or from SEC registration.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemptions from prohibition on Commission registration.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Transition rules.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.203A-6</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Amendments to Form ADV</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Books and records to be maintained by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Delivery of brochures and brochure supplements.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Reporting by exempt reporting advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204(b)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Reporting by investment advisers to private funds.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.204A-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Investment adviser codes of ethics.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.205-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “investment performance” of an investment company and “investment record” of an appropriate index of securities prices.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.205-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “specified period” over which the asset value of the company or fund under management is averaged.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.205-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemption from the compensation prohibition of section 205(a)(1) for investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(3)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemption of investment advisers registered as broker-dealers in connection with the provision of certain investment advisory services.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(3)-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Agency cross transactions for advisory clients.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Advertisements by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Custody of funds or securities of clients by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Cash payments for client solicitations.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Political contributions by certain investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-6</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Proxy voting.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-7</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Compliance procedures and practices.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.206(4)-8</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Pooled investment vehicles.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.222-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
            <SECTNO>275.222-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “client” for purposes of the national de mimimis standard.</SUBJECT>
        </CONTENTS>
        <AUTH>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
            <P>15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(11)(G), 80b-2(a)(11)(H), 80b-2(a)(17), 80b-3, 80b-4, 80b-4a, 80b-6(4), 80b-6a, and 80b-11, unless otherwise noted.</P>
            <P>Section 275.203A-1 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-3a.</P>
            <P>Section 275.203A-2 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-3a.</P>
            <P>Section 275.203A-3 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-3a.</P>
            <P>Section 275.203A-5 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-3a.</P>
            <P>Section 275.204-1 is also issued under sec. 407 and 408, Pub. L. 111-203, 124 Stat. 1376.</P>
            <P>Section 275.204-2 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-6.</P>
            <P>Section 275.205-3 is also issued under 15 U.S.C. 80b-5(e).</P>
            <P>Section 275.204-4 is also issued under sec. 407 and 408, Pub. L. 111-203, 124 Stat. 1376.</P>
        </AUTH>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>General procedures for serving non-residents.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">General procedures for serving process, pleadings, or other papers on non-resident investment advisers, general partners and managing agents.</E>Under Forms ADV and ADV-NR [17 CFR 279.1 and 279.4], a person may serve process, pleadings, or other papers on a non-resident investment adviser, or on a non-resident general partner or non-resident managing agent of an investment adviser by serving any or all of its appointed agents:</P>
            <P>(1) A person may serve a non-resident investment adviser, non-resident general partner, or non-resident managing agent by furnishing the Commission with one copy of the process, pleadings, or papers, for each named party, and one additional copy for the Commission's records.</P>
            <P>(2) If process, pleadings, or other papers are served on the Commission as described in this section, the Secretary of the Commission (Secretary) will promptly forward a copy to each named party by registered or certified mail at that party's last address filed with the Commission.</P>
            <P>(3) If the Secretary certifies that the Commission was served with process, pleadings, or other papers pursuant to paragraph (a)(1) of this section and forwarded these documents to a named party pursuant to paragraph (a)(2) of this section, this certification constitutes evidence of service upon that party.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definitions.</E>(b)For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Managing agent</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="937"/>means any person, including a trustee, who directs ormanages, or who participates in directing or managing, the affairs of any unincorporated organization or association other than a partnership.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Non-resident</E>(2)means:</P>
            <P>(i) An individual who resides in any place not subject to the jurisdiction of the United States;</P>
            <P>(ii) A corporation that is incorporated in or that has its principal office and place of business in any place not subject to the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
            <P>(iii) A partnership or other unincorporated organization or association that has its principal office and place of business in any place not subject to the jurisdiction of the United States.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Principal office and place of business</E>has the same meaning as in § 275.203A-3(c) of this chapter.</P>
            <CITA>[65 FR 57448, Sept. 22, 2000]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>References to rules and regulations.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">rules and regulations</E>The termrefers to all rules and regulations adopted by the Commission pursuant to the Act, including the forms for registration and reports and the accompanying instructions thereto.</P>
            <CITA>[30 FR 4129, Mar. 30, 1965]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>General requirements of papers and applications.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Filings.</E>(1) All papers required to be filed with the Commission shall, unless otherwise provided by the rules and regulations, be delivered through the mails or otherwise to the Securities and Exchange Commission, Washington, DC 20549. Except as otherwise provided by the rules and regulations, such papers shall be deemed to have been filed with the Commission on the date when they are actually received by it.</P>
            <P>(2) All filings required to be made electronically with the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (“IARD”) shall, unless otherwise provided by the rules and regulations in this part, be deemed to have been filed with the Commission upon acceptance by the IARD. Filings required to be made through the IARD on a day that the IARD is closed shall be considered timely filed with the Commission if filed with the IARD no later than the following business day.</P>
            <P>(3) Filings required to be made through the IARD during the period in December of each year that the IARD is not available for submission of filings shall be considered timely filed with the Commission if filed with the IARD no later than the following January 7.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">a</E>)(3):</HD>
                <P>
                    <E T="03">http://www.sec.gov/iard</E>Each year the IARD shuts down to filers for several days during the end of December to process renewals of state notice filings and registrations. During this period, advisers are not able to submit filings through the IARD. Check the Commission's Web site atfor the dates of the annual IARD shutdown.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Formal specifications respecting applications.</E>Every application for an order under any provision of the Act, for which a form with instructions is not specifically prescribed, and every amendment to such application, shall be filed in quintuplicate. One copy shall be signed by the applicant, but the other four copies may have facsimile or typed signatures. Such applications shall be on paper no larger than 8<FR>1/2</FR>×11 inches in size. To the extent that the reduction of larger documents would render them illegible, those documents may be filed on paper larger than 8<FR>1/2</FR>
                <FR>1/2</FR>×11 inches in size. The left margin should be at least 1inches wide and, if the application is bound, it should be bound on the left side. All typewritten or printed matter (including deficits in financial statements) should be set forth in black so as to permit photocopying and microfilming.</P>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">Authorization respecting applications.</E>(c)<PRTPAGE P="938"/>(1) Every application for an order under any provision of the Act, for which a form with instructions is not specifically prescribed and which is executed by a corporation, partnership, or other company and filed with the Commission, shall contain a concise statement of the applicable provisions of the articles of incorporation, bylaws, or similar documents, relating to the right of the person signing and filing such application to take such action on behalf of the applicant, and a statement that all such requirements have been complied with and that the personsigning and filing the same is fully authorized to do so. If such authorization is dependent on resolutions of stockholders, directors, or other bodies, such resolutions shall be attached as an exhibit to, or the pertinent provisions thereof shall be quoted in, the application.</P>
            <P>(2) If an amendment to any such application shall be filed, such amendment shall contain a similar statement or, in lieu thereof, shall state that the authorization described in the original application is applicable to the individual who signs such amendment and that such authorization still remains in effect.</P>
            <P>(3) When any such application or amendment is signed by an agent or attorney, the power of attorney evidencing his authority to sign shall contain similar statements and shall be filed with the Commission.</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Verification of applications and statements of fact.</E>Every application for an order under any provision of the Act, for which a form with instructions is not specifically prescribed and every amendment to such application, and every statement of fact formally filed in support of, or in opposition to, any application or declaration shall be verified by the person executing the same. An instrument executed on behalf of a corporation shall be verified in substantially the following form, but suitable changes may be made in such form for other kinds of companies and for individuals:</P>
            <EXTRACT>
                <P>State of __________________ County of __________, SS:______</P>
                <P>The undersigned being duly sworn deposes and says that he has duly executed the attached __________ dated _____, 19__, for and on behalf of ____________ (Name of company); that he is the ________ (Title of officer) of such company; and that all action by stockholders, directors, and other bodies necessary to authorize deponent to execute and file such instrument has been taken. Deponent further says that he is familiar with such instrument, and the contents thereof, and that the facts therein set forth are true to the best of his knowledge, information and belief.</P>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">(Signature)</FP>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-DASH">(Type or print name beneath)</FP>
                <P>Subscribed and sworn to before me a __________ (Title of officer) this _____ day of _____, 19__.</P>
                <P>[<E T="04">official seal</E>]</P>
                <P>My commission expires______</P>
            </EXTRACT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Statement of grounds for application.</E>(e)Each application should contain a brief statement of the reasons why the applicant is deemed to be entitled to the action requested with a reference to the provisions of the Act and of the rules and regulations under which application is made.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Name and address.</E>(f)Every application shall contain the name and address of each applicant and the name and address of any person to whom any applicant wishes any question regarding the application to be directed.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Proposed notice.</E>(g)A proposed notice of the proceeding initiated by the filing of the application shall accompany each application as an exhibit thereto and, if necessary, shall be modified to reflect any amendments to such application.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definition of application.</E>(h)For purposes of this rule, an “application” means any application for an order of the Commission under the Act other than an application for registration as an investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(i) The manually signed original (or in the case of duplicate original) one duplicate originals of all registrations, applications, statements, reports, or other documents filed under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940, as amended, shall be numbered sequentially (in addition to any internal numbering which otherwise may be present) by handwritten, typed, printed, or other legible form of notation from the facing page of the document through the last page of that document and any exhibits or attachments thereto. Further, the total number of pages contained in a numbered original shall be set forth on the first page of the document.</P>
            <CITA>[41 FR 39019, Sept. 14, 1976, as amended at 44 FR 4666, Jan. 23, 1979; 47 FR 58239, Dec. 30, 1982; 68 FR 42248, July 17, 2003; 76 FR 71877, Nov. 21, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Procedure with respect to applications and other matters.</SUBJECT>

            <P>The procedure hereinbelow set forth will be followed with respect to any proceeding initiated by the filing of an application, or upon the Commission's own motion, pursuant to any section of<PRTPAGE P="939"/>the Act or any rule or regulation thereunder, unless in the particular case a different procedure is provided:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="04">Federal Register</E>(a) Notice of the initiation of the proceeding will be published in theand will indicate the earliest date upon which an order disposing of the matter may be entered. The notice will also provide that any interested person may, within the period of time specified therein, submit to the Commission in writing any facts bearing upon the desirability of a hearing on the matter and may request that a hearing be held, stating his reasons therefor and the nature of his interest in the matter.</P>
            <P>(b) An order disposing of the matter will be issued as of course following the expiration of the period of time referred to in paragraph (a) of this section, unless the Commission thereafter orders a hearing on the matter.</P>
            <P>(c) The Commission will order a hearing on the matter, if it appears that a hearing is necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of investors, (1) upon the request of any interested person or (2) upon its own motion.</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Definition of application.</E>For purposes of this rule, an “application” means any application for an order of the Commission under the Act other than an application for registration as an investment adviser.</P>
            <CITA>[41 FR 39020, Sept. 14, 1976, as amended at 61 FR 49962, Sept. 24, 1996]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-6</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Incorporation by reference in applications.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) A person filing an application may, subject to the limitations of § 228.10(f) and § 229.10(d) of this chapter, incorporate by reference as an exhibit to such application any document or part thereof, including any financial statement or part thereof, previously or concurrently filed with the Commission pursuant to any act administered by the Commission. The incorporation may be made whether the matter incorporated was filed by such applicant or any other person. If any modification has occurred in the text of any such document since the filing thereof, the applicant shall file with the reference a statement containing the text of any such modification and the date thereof. If the number of copies of any document previously or concurrently filed with the Commission is less than the number required to be filed with the application which incorporates such document, the applicant shall file therewith as many additional copies of the document as may be necessary to meet the requirements of the application.</P>
            <P>(b) Notwithstanding paragraph (a) of this section, a certificate of an independent public accountant or accountants previously or concurrently filed may not be incorporated by reference in any application unless the written consent of the accountant or accountants to such incorporation is filed with the application.</P>
            <P>(c) In each case of incorporation by reference, the matter incorporated shall be clearly identified in the reference. An express statement shall be made to the effect that the specified matter is incorporated in the application at the particular place where the information is required.</P>
            <P>(d) Notwithstanding paragraph (a) of this section, no application shall incorporate by reference any exhibit or financial statement which (1) has been withdrawn, or (2) was filed under any act administered by the Commission in connection with a registration which has ceased to be effective, or (3) is contained in an application for registration, registration statement, or report subject, at the time of the incorporation by reference, to pending proceedings under section 8(b) (15 U.S.C. 77a-8(b)) or 8(d) (15 U.S.C. 77a-8(d)) of the Securities Act of 1933 (15 U.S.C. 77a-1 et seq.), section 8(e) (15 U.S.C. 80a-8(e)) of the Investment Company Act of 1940, section 15(b)(4)(A) (15 U.S.C. 78a-15(b)(4)(A)) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78a-1 et seq.), section 203(e)(1) (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(e)(1)) of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 or to an order entered under any of those sections.</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="940"/>(e) Notwithstanding paragraph (a) of this section, the Commission may refuse to permit incorporation by reference in any case in which in its judgment such incorporation would render an application incomplete, unclear, or confusing.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definition of Application.</E>(f)For purposes of this rule, an “application” means any application for an order of the Commission under the Act other than an application for registration as an investment adviser.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
                <P>Prior to incorporating by reference any document as an exhibit to an application, applicants are advised to review § 228.10(f) and § 229.10(d) of this chapter as in effect at the time the application is filed to determine whether such incorporation by reference would be permissible under that rule.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[41 FR 39020, Sept. 14, 1976, as amended at 60 FR 32825, June 23, 1995]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.0-7</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Small entities under the Investment Advisers Act for purposes of the Regulatory Flexibility Act.</SUBJECT>

            <P>(a) For purposes of Commission rulemaking in accordance with the provisions of Chapter Six of the Administrative Procedure Act (5 U.S.C. 601 et seq.) and unless otherwise defined for purposes of a particular rulemaking proceeding, the term<E T="03">small business</E>
                <E T="03">small organization</E>orfor purposes of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 shall mean an investment adviser that:</P>
            <P>(1) Has assets under management, as defined under Section 203A(a)(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)(2)) and reported on its annual updating amendment to Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1), of less than $25 million, or such higher amount as the Commission may by rule deem appropriate under Section 203A(a)(1)(A) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)(1)(A));</P>
            <P>(2) Did not have total assets of $5 million or more on the last day of the most recent fiscal year; and</P>
            <P>(3) Does not control, is not controlled by, and is not under common control with another investment adviser that has assets under management of $25 million or more (or such higher amount as the Commission may deem appropriate), or any person (other than a natural person) that had total assets of $5 million or more on the last day of the most recent fiscal year.</P>
            <P>(b) For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Control</E>(1)means the power, directly or indirectly, to direct the management or policies of a person, whether through ownership of securities, by contract, or otherwise.</P>
            <P>(i) A person is presumed to control a corporation if the person:</P>
            <P>(A) Directly or indirectly has the right to vote 25 percent or more of a class of the corporation's voting securities; or</P>
            <P>(B) Has the power to sell or direct the sale of 25 percent or more of a class of the corporation's voting securities.</P>
            <P>(ii) A person is presumed to control a partnership if the person has the right to receive upon dissolution, or has contributed, 25 percent or more of the capital of the partnership.</P>
            <P>(iii) A person is presumed to control a limited liability company (LLC) if the person:</P>
            <P>(A) Directly or indirectly has the right to vote 25 percent or more of a class of the interests of the LLC;</P>
            <P>(B) Has the right to receive upon dissolution, or has contributed, 25 percent or more of the capital of the LLC; or</P>
            <P>(C) Is an elected manager of the LLC.</P>
            <P>(iv) A person is presumed to control a trust if the person is a trustee or managing agent of the trust.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Total assets</E>means the total assets as shown on the balance sheet of the investment adviser or other person described above under paragraph (a)(3) of this section, or the balance sheet of the investment adviser or such other person with its subsidiaries consolidated, whichever is larger.</P>
            <CITA>[63 FR 35515, June 30, 1998, as amended at 65 FR 57448, Sept. 22, 2000; 76 FR 43011, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.202(a)(1)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Certain transactions not deemed assignments.</SUBJECT>
            <P>A transaction which does not result in a change of actual control or management of an investment adviser is not an assignment for purposes of section 205(a)(2) of the Act.</P>
            <CITA>[51 FR 32907, Sept. 17, 1986; 64 FR 2567, Jan. 15, 1999]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.202(a)(11)(G)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Family offices.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Exclusion.</E>A family office, as defined in this section, shall not be considered to be an investment adviser for purpose of the Act.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Family office.</E>A family office is a company (including its directors, partners, members, managers, trustees, and employees acting within the scope of their position or employment) that:</P>

            <P>(1) Has no clients other than family clients; provided that if a person that<PRTPAGE P="941"/>is not a family client becomes a client of the family office as a result of the death of a family member or key employee or other involuntary transfer from a family member or key employee, that person shall be deemed to be a family client for purposes of this section for one year following the completion of the transfer of legal title to the assets resulting from the involuntary event;</P>
            <P>(2) Is wholly owned by family clients and is exclusively controlled (directly or indirectly) by one or more family members and/or family entities; and</P>
            <P>(3) Does not hold itself out to the public as an investment adviser.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Grandfathering.</E>(c)A family office as defined in paragraph (a) of this section shall not exclude any person, who was not registered or required to be registered under the Act on January 1, 2010, solely because such person provides investment advice to, and was engaged before January 1, 2010 in providing investment advice to:</P>
            <P>(1) Natural persons who, at the time of their applicable investment, are officers, directors, or employees of the family office who have invested with the family office before January 1, 2010 and are accredited investors, as defined in Regulation D under the Securities Act of 1933;</P>
            <P>(2) Any company owned exclusively and controlled by one or more family members; or</P>
            <P>(3) Any investment adviser registered under the Act that provides investment advice to the family office and who identifies investment opportunities to the family office, and invests in such transactions on substantially the same terms as the family office invests, but does not invest in other funds advised by the family office, and whose assets as to which the family office directly or indirectly provides investment advice represents, in the aggregate, not more than 5 percent of the value of the total assets as to which the family office provides investment advice; provided that a family office that would not be a family office but for this paragraph (c) shall be deemed to be an investment adviser for purposes of paragraphs (1), (2) and (4) of section 206 of the Act.</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Affiliated family office</E>(1)means a family office wholly owned by family clients of another family office and that is controlled (directly or indirectly) by one or more family members of such other family office and/or family entities affiliated with such other family office and has no clients other than family clients of such other family office.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Control</E>(2)means the power to exercise a controlling influence over the management or policies of a company, unless such power is solely the result of being an officer of such company.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Executive officer</E>means the president, any vice president in charge of a principal business unit, division or function (such as administration or finance), any other officer who performs a policy-making function, or any other person who performs similar policy-making functions, for the family office.</P>
            <P>(4)<E T="03">Family client</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) Any family member;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any former family member;</P>
            <P>(iii) Any key employee;</P>
            <P>(iv) Any former key employee, provided that upon the end of such individual's employment by the family office, the former key employee shall not receive investment advice from the family office (or invest additional assets with a family office-advised trust, foundation or entity) other than with respect to assets advised (directly or indirectly) by the family office immediately prior to the end of such individual's employment, except that a former key employee shall be permitted to receive investment advice from the family office with respect to additional investments that the former key employee was contractually obligated to make, and that relate to a family-office advised investment existing, in each case prior to the time the person became a former key employee.</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="942"/>(v) Any non-profit organization, charitable foundation, charitable trust (including charitable lead trusts and charitable remainder trusts whose only current beneficiaries are other family clients and charitable or non-profit organizations), or other charitable organization, in each case for which all thefunding such foundation, trust or organization holds came exclusively from one or more other family clients;</P>
            <P>(vi) Any estate of a family member, former family member, key employee, or, subject to the condition contained in paragraph (d)(4)(iv) of this section, former key employee;</P>
            <P>(vii) Any irrevocable trust in which one or more other family clients are the only current beneficiaries;</P>
            <P>(viii) Any irrevocable trust funded exclusively by one or more other family clients in which other family clients and non-profit organizations, charitable foundations, charitable trusts, or other charitable organizations are the only current beneficiaries;</P>
            <P>(ix) Any revocable trust of which one or more other family clients are the sole grantor;</P>
            <P>(x) Any trust of which: Each trustee or other person authorized to make decisions with respect to the trust is a key employee; and each settlor or other person who has contributed assets to the trust is a key employee or the key employee's current and/or former spouse or spousal equivalent who, at the time of contribution, holds a joint, community property, or other similar shared ownership interest with the key employee; or</P>
            <P>(xi) Any company wholly owned (directly or indirectly) exclusively by, and operated for the sole benefit of, one or more other family clients; provided that if any such entity is a pooled investment vehicle, it is excepted from the definition of “investment company” under the Investment Company Act of 1940.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Family entity</E>(5)means any of the trusts, estates, companies or other entities set forth in paragraphs (d)(4)(v), (vi), (vii), (viii), (ix), or (xi) of this section, but excluding key employees and their trusts from the definition of family client solely for purposes of this definition.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Family member</E>(6)means all lineal descendants (including by adoption, stepchildren, foster children, and individuals that were a minor when another family member became a legal guardian of that individual) of a common ancestor (who may be living or deceased), and such lineal descendants' spouses or spousal equivalents; provided that the common ancestor is no more than 10 generations removed from the youngest generation of family members.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Former family member</E>(7)means a spouse, spousal equivalent, or stepchild that was a family member but is no longer a family member due to a divorce or other similar event.</P>
            <P>(8)<E T="03">Key employee</E>means any natural person (including any key employee's spouse or spouse equivalent who holds a joint, community property, or other similar shared ownership interest with that key employee) who is an executive officer, director, trustee, general partner, or person serving in a similar capacity of the family office or its affiliated family office or any employee of the family office or its affiliated family office (other than an employee performing solely clerical, secretarial, or administrative functions with regard to the family office) who, in connection with his or her regular functions or duties, participates in the investment activities of the family office or affiliated family office, provided that such employee has been performing such functions and duties for or on behalf of the family office or affiliated family office, or substantially similar functions or duties for or on behalf of another company, for at least 12 months.</P>
            <P>(9)<E T="03">Spousal equivalent</E>means a cohabitant occupying a relationship generally equivalent to that of a spouse.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Transition.</E>(e)(1) Any company existing on July 21, 2011 that would qualify as a family office under this section but for it having as a client one or more non-profit organizations, charitable foundations, charitable trusts, or other charitable organizations that have received funding from one or more individuals or companies that are not family clients shall be deemed to be a family office under this section until December 31, 2013, provided that such non-profit or charitable organization(s) do not accept any additional funding from any non-family client after August 31, 2011 (other than funding received prior to December 31, 2013 and provided in fulfillment of any pledge made prior to August 31, 2011).</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="943"/>(2) Any company engaged in the business of providing investment advice, directly or indirectly, primarily tomembers of a single family on July 21, 2011, and that is not registered under the Act in reliance on section 203(b)(3) of this title on July 20, 2011, is exempt from registration as an investment adviser under this title until March 30, 2012, provided that the company:</P>
            <P>(i) During the course of the preceding twelve months, has had fewer than fifteen clients; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Neither holds itself out generally to the public as an investment adviser nor acts as an investment adviser to any investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a), or a company which has elected to be a business development company pursuant to section 54 of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-54) and has not withdrawn its election.</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 37994, June 29, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.202(a)(30)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Foreign private advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Client.</E>You may deem the following to be a single client for purposes of section 202(a)(30) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(30)):</P>
            <P>(1) A natural person, and:</P>
            <P>(i) Any minor child of the natural person;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any relative, spouse, spousal equivalent, or relative of the spouse or of the spousal equivalent of the natural person who has the same principal residence;</P>
            <P>(iii) All accounts of which the natural person and/or the persons referred to in this paragraph (a)(1) are the only primary beneficiaries; and</P>
            <P>(iv) All trusts of which the natural person and/or the persons referred to in this paragraph (a)(1) are the only primary beneficiaries;</P>
            <P>(2)(i) A corporation, general partnership, limited partnership, limited liability company, trust (other than a trust referred to in paragraph (a)(1)(iv) of this section), or other legal organization (any of which are referred to hereinafter as a “legal organization”) to which you provide investment advice based on its investment objectives rather than the individual investment objectives of its shareholders, partners, limited partners, members, or beneficiaries (any of which are referred to hereinafter as an “owner”); and</P>
            <P>(ii) Two or more legal organizations referred to in paragraph (a)(2)(i) of this section that have identical owners.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Special rules regarding clients.</E>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(1) You must count an owner as a client if you provide investment advisory services to the owner separate and apart from the investment advisory services you provide to the legal organization, provided, however, that the determination that an owner is a client will not affect the applicability of this section with regard to any other owner;</P>
            <P>(2) You are not required to count an owner as a client solely because you, on behalf of the legal organization, offer, promote, or sell interests in the legal organization to the owner, or report periodically to the owners as a group solely with respect to the performance of or plans for the legal organization's assets or similar matters;</P>
            <P>(3) A limited partnership or limited liability company is a client of any general partner, managing member or other person acting as investment adviser to the partnership or limited liability company;</P>
            <P>(4) You are not required to count a private fund as a client if you count any investor, as that term is defined in paragraph (c)(2) of this section, in that private fund as an investor in the United States in that private fund; and</P>
            <P>(5) You are not required to count a person as an investor, as that term is defined in paragraph (c)(2) of this section, in a private fund you advise if you count such person as a client in the United States.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">a</E>Note to paragraphs () and (<E T="01">b</E>):</HD>
                <P>These paragraphs are a safe harbor and are not intended to specify the exclusive method for determining who may be deemed a single client for purposes of section 202(a)(30) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(30)).</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>For purposes of section 202(a)(30) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(30)):</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Assets under management</E>(1)means the regulatory assets under management as determined under Item 5.F of Form ADV (§ 279.1 of this chapter).</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Investor</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="944"/>means:</P>
            <P>(i) Any person who would be included in determining the number of beneficial owners of the outstanding securities of a private fund under section 3(c)(1) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(1)), or whether the outstanding securities of a private fund are owned exclusively by qualified purchasers under section 3(c)(7) of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(7)); and</P>
            <P>(ii) Any beneficial owner of any outstanding short-term paper, as defined in section 2(a)(38) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(38)), issued by the private fund.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">c</E>)(2):</HD>
                <P>You may treat as a single investor any person who is an investor in two or more private funds you advise.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">In the United States</E>means with respect to:</P>
            <P>(i) Any client or investor, any person who is a U.S. person as defined in § 230.902(k) of this chapter, except that any discretionary account or similar account that is held for the benefit of a person in the United States by a dealer or other professional fiduciary is in the United States if the dealer or professional fiduciary is a related person, as defined in § 275.206(4)-2(d)(7), of the investment adviser relying on this section and is not organized, incorporated, or (if an individual) resident in the United States.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">c</E>Note to paragraph (<E T="01">i</E>)(3)():</HD>
                <P>A person who is in the United States may be treated as not being in the United States if such person was not in the United States at the time of becoming a client or, in the case of an investor in a private fund, each time the investor acquires securities issued by the fund.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>
                <E T="03">in the United States,</E>(ii) Any place of business,as that term is defined in § 230.902(l) of this chapter; and</P>
            <P>(iii) The public,<E T="03">in the United States,</E>as that term is defined in § 230.902(l) of this chapter.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Place of business</E>(4)has the same meaning as in § 275.222-1(a).</P>
            <P>(5)<E T="03">Spousal equivalent</E>has the same meaning as in § 275.202(a)(11)(G)-1(d)(9).</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Holding out.</E>If you are relying on this section, you shall not be deemed to be holding yourself out generally to the public in the United States as an investment adviser, within the meaning of section 202(a)(30) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(30)), solely because you participate in a non-public offering in the United States of securities issued by a private fund under the Securities Act of 1933 (15 U.S.C. 77a).</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 39701, July 6, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Application for investment adviser registration.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Form ADV.</E>(a)Subject to paragraph (b), to apply for registration with the Commission as an investment adviser, you must complete Form ADV [17 CFR 279.1] by following the instructions in the form and you must file Part 1A of Form ADV and the firm brochure(s) required by Part 2A of Form ADV electronically with the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD) unless you have received a hardship exemption under § 275.203-3. You are not required to file with the Commission the brochure supplements required by Part 2B of Form ADV.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Transition to electronic filing.</E>If you apply for registration after January 1, 2011, you must file a brochure(s) that satisfies the requirements of Part 2A of Form ADV electronically with the IARD, unless you have received a continuing hardship exemption under § 275.203-3.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">a</E>Note to paragraphs (<E T="01">b</E>) and ():</HD>

                <P>Information on how to file with the IARD is available on the Commission's Web site at<E T="03">http://www.sec.gov/iard</E>. If you are not required to deliver a brochure to any clients, you are not required to prepare or file a brochure with the Commission. If you are not required to deliver a brochure supplement to any clients for any particular supervised person, you are not required to prepare a brochure supplement for that supervised person.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">When filed.</E>Each Form ADV is considered filed with the Commission upon acceptance by the IARD.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Filing fees.</E>(d)You must pay FINRA (the operator of the IARD) a filing fee. The Commission has approved the amount of the filing fee. No portion of the filing fee is refundable. Your completed application for registration will not be accepted by FINRA, and thus will not be considered filed with the Commission, until you have paid the filing fee.</P>
            <P>(e)<E T="03">“Private adviser” transition rule.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="945"/>If you are exempt from registration withthe Commission as an investment adviser under, and are not registered in reliance on, section 203(b)(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)) on July 20, 2011, you are exempt from registration with the Commission as an investment adviser until March 30, 2012, provided that you:</P>
            <P>(1) During the course of the preceding twelve months, have had fewer than fifteen clients; and</P>
            <P>(2) Neither hold yourself out generally to the public as an investment adviser nor act as an investment adviser to any investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a), or a company which has elected to be a business development company pursuant to section 54 of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-54) and has not withdrawn its election.</P>
            <CITA>[65 FR 57448, Sept. 22, 2000; 65 FR 81737, Dec. 27, 2000; 68 FR 42248, July 17, 2003; 73 FR 4694, Jan. 28, 2008; 75 FR 49267, Aug. 12, 2010; 76 FR 43011, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
            <EDNOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
                <P>
                    <E T="04">Federal Register</E>For<E T="03">www.fdsys.gov</E>citations affecting Form ADV, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at.</P>
            </EDNOTE>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Withdrawal from investment adviser registration.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Form ADV-W.</E>You must file Form ADV-W (17 CFR 279.2) to withdraw from investment adviser registration with the Commission (or to withdraw a pending registration application).</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Electronic filing.</E>Once you have filed your Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) (or any amendments to Form ADV) electronically with the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD), any Form ADV-W you file must be filed with the IARD, unless you have received a hardship exemption under § 275.203-3.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Effective date—upon filing.</E>(c)Each Form ADV-W filed under this section is effective upon acceptance by the IARD, provided however that your investment adviser registration will continue for a period of sixty days after acceptance solely for the purpose of commencing a proceeding under section 203(e) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(e)).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Filing fees.</E>(d)You do not have to pay a fee to file Form ADV-W through the IARD.</P>
            <P>(e)<E T="03">Form ADV-W is a report.</E>Each Form ADV-W required to be filed under this section is a “report” within the meaning of sections 204 and 207 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-4 and 80b-7).</P>
            <CITA>[65 FR 57449, Sept. 22, 2000]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Hardship exemptions.</SUBJECT>
            <P>This section provides two “hardship exemptions” from the requirement to make Advisers Act filings electronically with the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Temporary hardship exemption</E>(a)—(1)<E T="03">Eligibility for exemption.</E>If you are registered or are registering with the Commission as an investment adviser and submit electronic filings on the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD) system, but have unanticipated technical difficulties that prevent you from submitting a filing to the IARD system, you may request a temporary hardship exemption from the requirements of this chapter to file electronically.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Application procedures.</E>(2)To request a temporary hardship exemption, you must:</P>
            <P>(i) File Form ADV-H (17 CFR 279.3) in paper format with no later than one business day after the filing that is the subject of the ADV-H was due; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Submit the filing that is the subject of the Form ADV-H in electronic format with the IARD no later than seven business days after the filing was due.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Effective date—upon filing.</E>(3)The temporary hardship exemption will be granted when you file a completed Form ADV-H.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Continuing hardship exemption</E>
                <E T="03">Eligibility for exemption.</E>—(1)If you are a “small business” (as described in paragraph (b)(5) of this section), you may apply for a continuing hardship exemption.</P>
            <P>The period of the exemption may be no longer than one year after the date on which you apply for the exemption.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Application procedures.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="946"/>To apply for a continuing hardship exemption, you must file Form ADV-H at least ten business days before a filing is due. The Commission will grant or deny your application within ten business days after you file Form ADV-H.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Effective date—upon approval.</E>You are not exempt from the electronic filing requirements until and unless the Commission approves your application. If the Commission approves your application, you may submit your filings to FINRA in paper format for the period of time for which the exemption is granted.</P>
            <P>(4)<E T="03">Criteria for exemption.</E>Your application will be granted only if you are able to demonstrate that the electronic filing requirements of this chapter are prohibitively burdensome or expensive.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Small business.</E>(5)You are a “small business” for purposes of this section if you are required to answer Item 12 of Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) and checked “no” to each question in Item 12 that you were required to answer.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">b</E>Note to paragraph ():</HD>
                <P>FINRA will charge you an additional fee covering its cost to convert to electronic format a filing made in reliance on a continuing hardship exemption.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[65 FR 57449, Sept. 22, 2000; 65 FR 81738, Dec. 27, 2000, as amended at 68 FR 42248, July 17, 2003; 73 FR 4694, Jan. 28, 2008]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203(l)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Venture capital fund defined.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Venture capital fund defined.</E>(a)For purposes of section 203(l) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(l)), a venture capital fund is any private fund that:</P>
            <P>(1) Represents to investors and potential investors that it pursues a venture capital strategy;</P>
            <P>(2) Immediately after the acquisition of any asset, other than qualifying investments or short-term holdings, holds no more than 20 percent of the amount of the fund's aggregate capital contributions and uncalled committed capital in assets (other than short-term holdings) that are not qualifying investments, valued at cost or fair value, consistently applied by the fund;</P>
            <P>(3) Does not borrow, issue debt obligations, provide guarantees or otherwise incur leverage, in excess of 15 percent of the private fund's aggregate capital contributions and uncalled committed capital, and any such borrowing, indebtedness, guarantee or leverage is for a non-renewable term of no longer than 120 calendar days, except that any guarantee by the private fund of a qualifying portfolio company's obligations up to the amount of the value of the private fund's investment in the qualifying portfolio company is not subject to the 120 calendar day limit;</P>
            <P>(4) Only issues securities the terms of which do not provide a holder with any right, except in extraordinary circumstances, to withdraw, redeem or require the repurchase of such securities but may entitle holders to receive distributions made to all holders pro rata; and</P>
            <P>(5) Is not registered under section 8 of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-8), and has not elected to be treated as a business development company pursuant to section 54 of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-53).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Certain pre-existing venture capital funds.</E>(b)For purposes of section 203(l) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(l)) and in addition to any venture capital fund as set forth in paragraph (a) of this section, a venture capital fund also includes any private fund that:</P>
            <P>(1) Has represented to investors and potential investors at the time of the offering of the private fund's securities that it pursues a venture capital strategy;</P>
            <P>(2) Prior to December 31, 2010, has sold securities to one or more investors that are not related persons, as defined in § 275.206(4)-2(d)(7), of any investment adviser of the private fund; and</P>
            <P>(3) Does not sell any securities to (including accepting any committed capital from) any person after July 21, 2011.</P>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Committed capital</E>(1)means any commitment pursuant to which a person is obligated to:</P>
            <P>(i) Acquire an interest in the private fund; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Make capital contributions to the private fund.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Equity security</E>(2)has the same meaning as in section 3(a)(11) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(11)) and § 240.3a11-1 of this chapter.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Qualifying investment</E>(3)means:</P>

            <P>(i) An equity security issued by a qualifying portfolio company that has been acquired directly by the private fund from the qualifying portfolio company;<PRTPAGE P="947"/>
            </P>
            <P>(ii) Any equity security issued by a qualifying portfolio company in exchange for an equity security issued by the qualifying portfolio company described in paragraph (c)(3)(i) of this section; or</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">equity security</E>(iii) Any equity security issued by a company of which a qualifying portfolio company is a majority-owned subsidiary, as defined in section 2(a)(24) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(24)), or a predecessor, and is acquired by the private fund in exchange for andescribed in paragraph (c)(3)(i) or (c)(3)(ii) of this section.</P>
            <P>(4)<E T="03">Qualifying portfolio company</E>means any company that:</P>
            <P>(i) At the time of any investment by the private fund, is not reporting or foreign traded and does not control, is not controlled by or under common control with another company, directly or indirectly, that is reporting or foreign traded;</P>
            <P>(ii) Does not borrow or issue debt obligations in connection with the private fund's investment in such company and distribute to the private fund the proceeds of such borrowing or issuance in exchange for the private fund's investment; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Is not an investment company, a private fund, an issuer that would be an investment company but for the exemption provided by § 270.3a-7 of this chapter, or a commodity pool.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Reporting or foreign traded</E>(5)means, with respect to a company, being subject to the reporting requirements under section 13 or 15(d) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78m or 78o(d)), or having a security listed or traded on any exchange or organized market operating in a foreign jurisdiction.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Short-term holdings</E>(6)means cash and cash equivalents, as defined in § 270.2a51-1(b)(7)(i) of this chapter, U.S. Treasuries with a remaining maturity of 60 days or less, and shares of an open-end management investment company registered under section 8 of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-8) that is regulated as a money market fund under § 270.2a-7 of this chapter.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
                <P>For purposes of this section, an investment adviser may treat as a private fund any issuer formed under the laws of a jurisdiction other than the United States that has not offered or sold its securities in the United States or to U.S. persons in a manner inconsistent with being a private fund, provided that the adviser treats the issuer as a private fund under the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b) and the rules thereunder for all purposes.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[76 FR 39702, July 6, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203(m)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Private fund adviser exemption.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">United States investment advisers.</E>(a)For purposes of section 203(m) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(m)), an investment adviser with its principal office and place of business in the United States is exempt from the requirement to register under section 203 of the Act if the investment adviser:</P>
            <P>(1) Acts solely as an investment adviser to one or more qualifying private funds; and</P>
            <P>(2) Manages private fund assets of less than $150 million.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Non-United States investment advisers.</E>For purposes of section 203(m) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(m)), an investment adviser with its principal office and place of business outside of the United States is exempt from the requirement to register under section 203 of the Act if:</P>
            <P>(1) The investment adviser has no client that is a United States person except for one or more qualifying private funds; and</P>
            <P>(2) All assets managed by the investment adviser at a place of business in the United States are solely attributable to private fund assets, the total value of which is less than $150 million.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Frequency of Calculations.</E>(c)For purposes of this section, calculate private fund assets annually, in accordance with General Instruction 15 to Form ADV (§ 279.1 of this chapter).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definitions.</E>(d)For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Assets under management</E>(1)means the regulatory assets under management as determined under Item 5.F of Form ADV (§ 279.1 of this chapter).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Place of business</E>(2)has the same meaning as in § 275.222-1(a).</P>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">Principal office and place of business</E>(3)<PRTPAGE P="948"/>of an investment adviser means the executive office of the investment adviser from which the officers, partners, or managers of the investmentadviser direct, control, and coordinate the activities of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Private fund assets</E>(4)means the investment adviser's assets under management attributable to a qualifying private fund.</P>
            <P>(5)<E T="03">Qualifying private fund</E>means any private fund that is not registered under section 8 of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-8) and has not elected to be treated as a business development company pursuant to section 54 of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-53). For purposes of this section, an investment adviser may treat as a private fund an issuer that qualifies for an exclusion from the definition of an “investment company,” as defined in section 3 of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-3), in addition to those provided by section 3(c)(1) or 3(c)(7) of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(1) or 15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(7)), provided that the investment adviser treats the issuer as a private fund under the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b) and the rules thereunder for all purposes.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Related person</E>(6)has the same meaning as in § 275.206(4)-2(d)(7).</P>
            <P>(7)<E T="03">United States</E>has the same meaning as in § 230.902(l) of this chapter.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">United States person</E>(8)means any person that is a U.S. person as defined in § 230.902(k) of this chapter, except that any discretionary account or similar account that is held for the benefit of a United States person by a dealer or other professional fiduciary is a United States person if the dealer or professional fiduciary is a related person of the investment adviser relying on this section and is not organized, incorporated, or (if an individual) resident in the United States.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraph (<E T="01">d</E>)(8):</HD>
                <P>A client will not be considered a United States person if the client was not a United States person at the time of becoming a client.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[76 FR 39703, July 6, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Eligibility for SEC registration; Switching to or from SEC registration.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Eligibility for SEC registration of mid-sized investment advisers.</E>(a)If you are an investment adviser described in section 203A(a)(2)(B) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)(2)(B)):</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Threshold for SEC registration and registration buffer.</E>(1)You may, but are not required to register with the Commission if you have assets under management of at least $100,000,000 but less than $110,000,000, and you need not withdraw your registration unless you have less than $90,000,000 of assets under management.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Exceptions.</E>(2)This paragraph (a) does not apply if:</P>
            <P>(i) You are an investment adviser to an investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a) or to a company which has elected to be a business development company pursuant to section 54 of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-54), and has not withdrawn the election; or</P>
            <P>(ii) You are eligible for an exemption described in § 275.203A-2 of this chapter.</P>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">Switching to or from SEC registration</E>(b)—(1)<E T="03">State-registered advisers—switching to SEC registration.</E>If you are registered with a state securities authority, you must apply for registration with the Commission within 90 days of filing an annual updating amendment to your Form ADV reporting that you are eligible for SEC registration and are not relying on an exemption from registration under sections 203(l) or 203(m) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(l), (m)).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">SEC-registered advisers—switching to State registration.</E>(2)If you are registered with the Commission and file an annual updating amendment to your Form ADV reporting that you are not eligible for SEC registration and are not relying on an exemption from registration under sections 203(l) or 203(m) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(l), (m)), you must file Form ADV-W (17 CFR 279.2) to withdraw your SEC registration within 180 days of your fiscal year end (unless you then are eligible for SEC registration). During this period while you are registered with both the Commission and one or more state securities authorities, the Act and applicable State law will apply to your advisory activities.</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 43011, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <PRTPAGE P="949"/>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemptions from prohibition on Commission registration.</SUBJECT>
            <P>The prohibition of section 203A(a) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)) does not apply to:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Pension consultants.</E>(a)(1) An investment adviser that is a “pension consultant,” as defined in this section, with respect to assets of plans having an aggregate value of at least $200,000,000.</P>
            <P>(2) An investment adviser is a pension consultant, for purposes of paragraph (a) of this section, if the investment adviser provides investment advice to:</P>
            <P>(i) Any employee benefit plan described in section 3(3) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (“ERISA”) [29 U.S.C. 1002(3)];</P>
            <P>(ii) Any governmental plan described in section 3(32) of ERISA (29 U.S.C. 1002(32)); or</P>
            <P>(iii) Any church plan described in section 3(33) of ERISA (29 U.S.C. 1002(33)).</P>
            <P>(3) In determining the aggregate value of assets of plans, include only that portion of a plan's assets for which the investment adviser provided investment advice (including any advice with respect to the selection of an investment adviser to manage such assets). Determine the aggregate value of assets by cumulating the value of assets of plans with respect to which the investment adviser was last employed or retained by contract to provide investment advice during a 12-month period ended within 90 days of filing an annual updating amendment to Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Investment advisers controlling, controlled by, or under common control with an investment adviser registered with the Commission.</E>(b)An investment adviser that controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with, an investment adviser eligible to register, and registered with, the Commission (“registered adviser”), provided that the principal office and place of business of the investment adviser is the same as that of the registered adviser. For purposes of this paragraph, control means the power to direct or cause the direction of the management or policies of an investment adviser, whether through ownership of securities, by contract, or otherwise. Any person that directly or indirectly has the right to vote 25 percent or more of the voting securities, or is entitled to 25 percent or more of the profits, of an investment adviser is presumed to control that investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">Investment advisers expecting to be eligible for Commission registration within 120 Days.</E>An investment adviser that:</P>
            <P>(1) Immediately before it registers with the Commission, is not registered or required to be registered with the Commission or a state securities authority of any State and has a reasonable expectation that it would be eligible to register with the Commission within 120 days after the date the investment adviser's registration with the Commission becomes effective;</P>
            <P>(2) Indicates on Schedule D of its Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) that it will withdraw from registration with the Commission if, on the 120th day after the date the investment adviser's registration with the Commission becomes effective, the investment adviser would be prohibited by section 203A(a) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)) from registering with the Commission; and</P>
            <P>(3) Notwithstanding § 275.203A-1(b)(2) of this chapter, files a completed Form ADV-W (17 CFR 279.2) withdrawing from registration with the Commission within 120 days after the date the investment adviser's registration with the Commission becomes effective.</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Multi-state investment advisers.</E>An investment adviser that:</P>
            <P>(1) Upon submission of its application for registration with the Commission, is required by the laws of 15 or more States to register as an investment adviser with the state securities authority in the respective States, and thereafter would, but for this section, be required by the laws of at least 15 States to register as an investment adviser with the state securities authority in the respective States;</P>
            <P>(2) Elects to rely on paragraph (d) of this section by:</P>

            <P>(i) Indicating on Schedule D of its Form ADV that the investment adviser has reviewed the applicable State and federal laws and has concluded that, in the case of an application for registration with the Commission, it is required by the laws of 15 or more States<PRTPAGE P="950"/>to register as an investment adviser with the state securities authorities in the respective States or, in the case of an amendment to Form ADV, it would be required by the laws of at least 15 States to register as an investment adviser with the state securities authorities in the respective States, within 90 days prior to the date of filing Form ADV; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Undertaking on Schedule D of its Form ADV to withdraw from registration with the Commission if the adviser indicates on an annual updating amendment to Form ADV that the investment adviser would be required by the laws of fewer than 15 States to register as an investment adviser with the state securities authority in the respective States, and that the investment adviser would be prohibited by section 203A(a) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)) from registering with the Commission, by filing a completed Form ADV-W within 180 days of the adviser's fiscal year end (unless the adviser then is eligible for SEC registration); and</P>
            <P>(3) Maintains in an easily accessible place a record of the States in which the investment adviser has determined it would, but for the exemption, be required to register for a period of not less than five years from the filing of a Form ADV that includes a representation that is based on such record.</P>
            <P>(e)<E T="03">Internet investment advisers.</E>(1) An investment adviser that:</P>
            <P>(i) Provides investment advice to all of its clients exclusively through an interactive website, except that the investment adviser may provide investment advice to fewer than 15 clients through other means during the preceding twelve months;</P>
            <P>(ii) Maintains, in an easily accessible place, for a period of not less than five years from the filing of a Form ADV that includes a representation that the adviser is eligible to register with the Commission under paragraph (e) of this section, a record demonstrating that it provides investment advice to its clients exclusively through an interactive website in accordance with the limits in paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section; and</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">registered adviser.</E>(iii) Does not control, is not controlled by, and is not under common control with, another investment adviser that registers with the Commission under paragraph (b) of this section solely in reliance on the adviser registered under paragraph (e) of this section as its</P>
            <P>(2) For purposes of paragraph (e) of this section,<E T="03">interactive website</E>means a website in which computer software-based models or applications provide investment advice to clients based on personal information each client supplies through the website.</P>
            <P>(3) An investment adviser may rely on the definition of<E T="03">client</E>in § 275.202(a)(30)-1 in determining whether it provides investment advice to fewer than 15 clients under paragraph (e)(1)(i) of this section.</P>
            <CITA>[62 FR 28133, May 22, 1997, as amended at 63 FR 39715, 39716, July 24, 1998; 65 FR 57450, Sept. 22, 2000; 67 FR 77625, Dec. 18, 2003; 76 FR 43012, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
            <P>For purposes of section 203A of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a) and the rules thereunder:</P>
            <P>(a)(1)<E T="03">Investment adviser representative.</E>“Investment adviser representative” of an investment adviser means a supervised person of the investment adviser:</P>
            <P>(i) Who has more than five clients who are natural persons (other than excepted persons described in paragraph (a)(3)(i) of this section); and</P>
            <P>(ii) More than ten percent of whose clients are natural persons (other than excepted persons described in paragraph (a)(3)(i) of this section).</P>
            <P>(2) Notwithstanding paragraph (a)(1) of this section, a supervised person is not an investment adviser representative if the supervised person:</P>
            <P>(i) Does not on a regular basis solicit, meet with, or otherwise communicate with clients of the investment adviser; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Provides only impersonal investment advice.</P>
            <P>(3) For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(i) “Excepted person” means a natural person who is a qualified client as described in § 275.205-3(d)(1).</P>

            <P>(ii) “Impersonal investment advice” means investment advisory services provided by means of written material or oral statements that do not purport<PRTPAGE P="951"/>to meet the objectives or needs of specific individuals or accounts.</P>
            <P>(4) Supervised persons may rely on the definition of “client” in § 275.202(a)(30)-1 to identify clients for purposes of paragraph (a)(1) of this section, except that supervised persons need not count clients that are not residents of the United States.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Place of business.</E>(b)“Place of business” of an investment adviser representative means:</P>
            <P>(1) An office at which the investment adviser representative regularly provides investment advisory services, solicits, meets with, or otherwise communicates with clients; and</P>
            <P>(2) Any other location that is held out to the general public as a location at which the investment adviser representative provides investment advisory services, solicits, meets with, or otherwise communicates with clients.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Principal office and place of business.</E>(c)“Principal office and place of business” of an investment adviser means the executive office of the investment adviser from which the officers, partners, or managers of the investment adviser direct, control, and coordinate the activities of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Assets under management.</E>Determine “assets under management” by calculating the securities portfolios with respect to which an investment adviser provides continuous and regular supervisory or management services as reported on the investment adviser's Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">State securities authority.</E>(e)“State securities authority” means the securities commissioner or commission (or any agency, office or officer performing like functions) of any State.</P>
            <CITA>[62 FR 28134, May 22, 1997, as amended at 63 FR 39715, July 24, 1998; 69 FR 72088, Dec. 10, 2004; 76 FR 43012, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-4</SECTNO>
            <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Transition rules.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Temporary exemption from prohibition on Commission registration for mid-sized investment advisers.</E>Until January 1, 2012, the prohibition of section 203A(a)(2) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)(2)) does not apply to an investment adviser registered with the Commission on July 21, 2011.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">SEC-registered advisers</E>(b)—<E T="03">Form ADV filing.</E>Every investment adviser registered with the Commission on January 1, 2012 shall file an amendment to Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) no later than March 30, 2012 and shall determine its assets under management based on the current market value of the assets as determined within 90 days prior to the date of filing the Form ADV.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Mid-sized investment advisers</E>(c)<E T="03">withdrawing from Commission registration.</E>—</P>
            <P>(1) If an investment adviser registered with the Commission on January 1, 2012 would be prohibited from registering with the Commission under section 203A(a)(2) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3a(a)(2)), and is not otherwise exempted by § 275.203A-2 from such prohibition, such investment adviser shall withdraw from registration with the Commission by filing Form ADV-W (17 CFR 279.2) no later than June 28, 2012. During this period while an investment adviser is registered with both the Commission and one or more state securities authorities, the Act and applicable State law will apply to the investment adviser's advisory activities.</P>
            <P>(2) If, prior to the effective date of the withdrawal from registration of an investment adviser on Form ADV-W, the Commission has instituted a proceeding pursuant to section 203(e) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(e)) to suspend or revoke registration, or pursuant to section 203(h) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(h)) to impose terms or conditions upon withdrawal, the withdrawal from registration shall not become effective except at such time and upon such terms and conditions as the Commission deems necessary or appropriate in the public interest or for the protection of investors.</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 43012, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.203A-6</SECTNO>
            <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Amendments to Form ADV.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">When amendment is required.</E>(a)You must amend your Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1):</P>
            <P>(1) At least annually, within 90 days of the end of your fiscal year; and</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="952"/>(2) More frequently, if required by the instructions to Form ADV.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Electronic filing of amendments.</E>(b)(1) Subject to paragraph (c) of this section, you must file all amendments to Part 1A of Form ADV and Part 2A of Form ADV electronically with the IARD, unless you have received a continuing hardship exemption under § 275.203-3. You are not required to file with the Commission amendments to brochure supplements required by Part 2B of Form ADV.</P>
            <P>(2) If you have received a continuing hardship exemption under § 275.203-3, you must, when you are required to amend your Form ADV, file a completed Part 1A and Part 2A of Form ADV on paper with the SEC by mailing it to FINRA.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note to paragraphs (<E T="01">a</E>
                    <E T="01">b</E>) and ():</HD>
                <P>
                    <E T="03">http://www.sec.gov/iard.</E>Information on how to file with the IARD is available on our Web site atFor the annual updating amendment: Summaries of material changes that are not included in the adviser's brochure must be filed with the Commission as an exhibit to Part 2A in the same electronic file; and if you are not required to prepare a brochure, a summary of material changes, or an annual updating amendment to your brochure, you are not required to file them with the Commission. See the instructions for Part 2A of Form ADV.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Transition to electronic filing.</E>(c)If you are required to file a brochure and your fiscal year ends on or after December 31, 2010, you must amend your Form ADV by electronically filing with the IARD one or more brochures that satisfy the requirements of Part 2A of Form ADV (as amended effective October 12, 2010) as part of the next annual updating amendment that you are required to file.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Filing fees.</E>(d)You must pay FINRA (the operator of the IARD) an initial filing fee when you first electronically file Part 1A of Form ADV. After you pay the initial filing fee, you must pay an annual filing fee each time you file your annual updating amendment. No portion of either fee is refundable. The Commission has approved the filing fees. Your amended Form ADV will not be accepted by FINRA, and thus will not be considered filed with the Commission, until you have paid the filing fee.</P>
            <P>(e)<E T="03">Amendments to Form ADV are reports.</E>Each amendment required to be filed under this section is a “report” within the meaning of sections 204 and 207 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-4 and 80b-7).</P>
            <CITA>[65 FR 57450, Sept. 22, 2000; 65 FR 81738, Dec. 27, 2000, as amended at 68 FR 42248, July 17, 2003; 73 FR 4694, Jan. 28, 2008; 75 FR 49267, Aug. 12, 2010; 76 FR 43013, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Books and records to be maintained by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) Every investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3) shall make and keep true, accurate and current the following books and records relating to its investment advisory business;</P>
            <P>(1) A journal or journals, including cash receipts and disbursements, records, and any other records of original entry forming the basis of entries in any ledger.</P>
            <P>(2) General and auxiliary ledgers (or other comparable records) reflecting asset, liability, reserve, capital, income and expense accounts.</P>
            <P>(3) A memorandum of each order given by the investment adviser for the purchase or sale of any security, of any instruction received by the investment adviser concerning the purchase, sale, receipt or delivery of a particular security, and of any modification or cancellation of any such order or instruction. Such memoranda shall show the terms and conditions of the order, instruction, modification or cancellation; shall identify the person connected with the investment adviser who recommended the transaction to the client and the person who placed such order; and shall show the account for which entered, the date of entry, and the bank, broker or dealer by or through whom executed where appropriate. Orders entered pursuant to the exercise of discretionary power shall be so designated.</P>
            <P>(4) All check books, bank statements, cancelled checks and cash reconciliations of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(5) All bills or statements (or copies thereof), paid or unpaid, relating to the business of the investment adviser as such.</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="953"/>(6) All trial balances, financial statements, and internal audit working papers relating to the business of such investment adviser.</P>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">Provided, however,</E>(7) Originals of all written communications received and copies of all written communications sent by such investment adviser relating to (i) any recommendation made or proposed to be made and any advice given or proposed to be given, (ii) any receipt, disbursement or delivery of funds or securities, or (iii) the placing or execution of any order to purchase or sell any security:(<E T="03">a</E>
                <E T="03">b</E>) That the investment adviser shall not be required to keep any unsolicited market letters and other similar communications of general public distribution not prepared by or for the investment adviser, and () that if the investment adviser sends any notice, circular or other advertisement offering any report, analysis, publication or other investment advisory service to more than 10 persons, the investment adviser shall not be required to keep a record of the names and addresses of the persons to whom it was sent; except that if such notice, circular or advertisement is distributed to persons named on any list, the investment adviser shall retain with the copy of such notice, circular or advertisement a memorandum describing the list and the source thereof.</P>
            <P>(8) A list or other record of all accounts in which the investment adviser is vested with any discretionary power with respect to the funds, securities or transactions of any client.</P>
            <P>(9) All powers of attorney and other evidences of the granting of any discretionary authority by any client to the investment adviser, or copies thereof.</P>
            <P>(10) All written agreements (or copies thereof) entered into by the investment adviser with any client or otherwise relating to the business of such investment adviser as such.</P>
            <P>(11) A copy of each notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin or other communication that the investment adviser circulates or distributes, directly or indirectly, to 10 or more persons (other than persons connected with such investment adviser), and if such notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin or other communication recommends the purchase or sale of a specific security and does not state the reasons for such recommendation, a memorandum of the investment adviser indicating the reasons therefor.</P>
            <P>(12)(i) A copy of the investment adviser's code of ethics adopted and implemented pursuant to § 275.204A-1 that is in effect, or at any time within the past five years was in effect;</P>
            <P>(ii) A record of any violation of the code of ethics, and of any action taken as a result of the violation; and</P>
            <P>(iii) A record of all written acknowledgments as required by § 275.204A-1(a)(5) for each person who is currently, or within the past five years was, a supervised person of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(13)(i) A record of each report made by an access person as required by § 275.204A-1(b), including any information provided under paragraph (b)(3)(iii) of that section in lieu of such reports;</P>
            <P>(ii) A record of the names of persons who are currently, or within the past five years were, access persons of the investment adviser; and</P>
            <P>(iii) A record of any decision, and the reasons supporting the decision, to approve the acquisition of securities by access persons under § 275.204A-1(c), for at least five years after the end of the fiscal year in which the approval is granted.</P>
            <P>(14)(i) A copy of each brochure and brochure supplement, and each amendment or revision to the brochure and brochure supplement, that satisfies the requirements of Part 2 of Form ADV [17 CFR 279.1]; any summary of material changes that satisfies the requirements of Part 2 of Form ADV but is not contained in the brochure; and a record of the dates that each brochure and brochure supplement, each amendment or revision thereto, and each summary of material changes not contained in a brochure was given to any client or to any prospective client who subsequently becomes a client.</P>
            <P>(ii) Documentation describing the method used to compute managed assets for purposes of Item 4.E of Part 2A of Form ADV, if the method differs from the method used to compute regulatory assets under management in Item 5.F of Part 1A of Form ADV.</P>

            <P>(iii) A memorandum describing any legal or disciplinary event listed in<PRTPAGE P="954"/>Item 9 of Part 2A or Item 3 of Part 2B (Disciplinary Information) and presumed to be material, if the event involved the investment adviser or any of its supervised persons and is not disclosed in the brochure or brochure supplement described in paragraph (a)(14)(i) of this section. The memorandum must explain the investment adviser's determination that the presumption of materiality is overcome, and must discuss the factors described in Item 9 of Part 2A of Form ADV or Item 3 of Part 2B of Form ADV.</P>
            <P>(15) All written acknowledgments of receipt obtained from clients pursuant to § 275.206(4)-3(a)(2)(iii)(B) and copies of the disclosure documents delivered to clients by solicitors pursuant to § 275.206(4)-3.</P>

            <P>(16) All accounts, books, internal working papers, and any other records or documents that are necessary to form the basis for or demonstrate the calculation of the performance or rate of return of any or all managed accounts or securities recommendations in any notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin or other communication that the investment adviser circulates or distributes, directly or indirectly, to 10 or more persons (other than persons connected with such investment adviser);<E T="03">provided, however,</E>that, with respect to the performance of managed accounts, the retention of all account statements, if they reflect all debits, credits, and other transactions in a client's account for the period of the statement, and all worksheets necessary to demonstrate the calculation of the performance or rate of return of all managed accounts shall be deemed to satisfy the requirements of this paragraph.</P>
            <P>(17)(i) A copy of the investment adviser's policies and procedures formulated pursuant to § 275.206(4)-7(a) of this chapter that are in effect, or at any time within the past five years were in effect;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any records documenting the investment adviser's annual review of those policies and procedures conducted pursuant to § 275.206(4)-7(b) of this chapter;</P>
            <P>(iii) A copy of any internal control report obtained or received pursuant to § 275. 206(4)-2(a)(6)(ii).</P>
            <P>(18)(i) Books and records that pertain to § 275.206(4)-5 containing a list or other record of:</P>
            <P>(A) The names, titles and business and residence addresses of all covered associates of the investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(B) All government entities to which the investment adviser provides or has provided investment advisory services, or which are or were investors in any covered investment pool to which the investment adviser provides or has provided investment advisory services, as applicable, in the past five years, but not prior to September 13, 2010;</P>
            <P>(C) All direct or indirect contributions made by the investment adviser or any of its covered associates to an official of a government entity, or direct or indirect payments to a political party of a State or political subdivision thereof, or to a political action committee; and</P>
            <P>(D) The name and business address of each regulated person to whom the investment adviser provides or agrees to provide, directly or indirectly, payment to solicit a government entity for investment advisory services on its behalf, in accordance with § 275.206(4)-5(a)(2).</P>
            <P>(ii) Records relating to the contributions and payments referred to in paragraph (a)(18)(i)(C) of this section must be listed in chronological order and indicate:</P>
            <P>(A) The name and title of each contributor;</P>
            <P>(B) The name and title (including any city/county/State or other political subdivision) of each recipient of a contribution or payment;</P>
            <P>(C) The amount and date of each contribution or payment; and</P>
            <P>(D) Whether any such contribution was the subject of the exception for certain returned contributions pursuant to § 275.206(4)-5(b)(2).</P>

            <P>(iii) An investment adviser is only required to make and keep current the records referred to in paragraphs (a)(18)(i)(A) and (C) of this section if it provides investment advisory services<PRTPAGE P="955"/>to a government entity or a government entity is an investor in any covered investment pool to which the investment adviser provides investment advisory services.</P>
            <P>(iv) For purposes of this section, the terms “contribution,” “covered associate,” “covered investment pool,” “government entity,” “official,” “payment,” “regulated person,” and “solicit” have the same meanings as set forth in § 275.206(4)-5.</P>
            <P>(b) If an investment adviser subject to paragraph (a) of this section has custody or possession of securities or funds of any client, the records required to be made and kept under paragraph (a) of this section shall include:</P>
            <P>(1) A journal or other record showing all purchases, sales, receipts and deliveries of securities (including certificate numbers) for such accounts and all other debits and credits to such accounts.</P>
            <P>(2) A separate ledger account for each such client showing all purchases, sales, receipts and deliveries of securities, the date and price of each purchase and sale, and all debits and credits.</P>
            <P>(3) Copies of confirmations of all transactions effected by or for the account of any such client.</P>
            <P>(4) A record for each security in which any such client has a position, which record shall show the name of each such client having any interest in such security, the amount or interest of each such client, and the location of each such security.</P>
            <P>(5) A memorandum describing the basis upon which you have determined that the presumption that any related person is not operationally independent under § 275.206(4)-2(d)(5) has been overcome.</P>
            <P>(c)(1) Every investment adviser subject to paragraph (a) of this section who renders any investment supervisory or management service to any client shall, with respect to the portfolio being supervised or managed and to the extent that the information is reasonably available to or obtainable by the investment adviser, make and keep true, accurate and current:</P>
            <P>(i) Records showing separately for each such client the securities purchased and sold, and the date, amount and price of each such purchase and sale.</P>
            <P>(ii) For each security in which any such client has a current position, information from which the investment adviser can promptly furnish the name of each such client, and the current amount or interest of such client.</P>
            <P>(2) Every investment adviser subject to paragraph (a) of this section that exercises voting authority with respect to client securities shall, with respect to those clients, make and retain the following:</P>
            <P>(i) Copies of all policies and procedures required by § 275.206(4)-6.</P>
            <P>(ii) A copy of each proxy statement that the investment adviser receives regarding client securities. An investment adviser may satisfy this requirement by relying on a third party to make and retain, on the investment adviser's behalf, a copy of a proxy statement (provided that the adviser has obtained an undertaking from the third party to provide a copy of the proxy statement promptly upon request) or may rely on obtaining a copy of a proxy statement from the Commission's Electronic Data Gathering, Analysis, and Retrieval (EDGAR) system.</P>
            <P>(iii) A record of each vote cast by the investment adviser on behalf of a client. An investment adviser may satisfy this requirement by relying on a third party to make and retain, on the investment adviser's behalf, a record of the vote cast (provided that the adviser has obtained an undertaking from the third party to provide a copy of the record promptly upon request).</P>
            <P>(iv) A copy of any document created by the adviser that was material to making a decision how to vote proxies on behalf of a client or that memorializes the basis for that decision.</P>
            <P>(v) A copy of each written client request for information on how the adviser voted proxies on behalf of the client, and a copy of any written response by the investment adviser to any (written or oral) client request for information on how the adviser voted proxies on behalf of the requesting client.</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="956"/>(d) Any books or records required by this section may be maintained by the investment adviser in such manner that the identity of any client to whomsuch investment adviser renders investment supervisory services is indicated by numerical or alphabetical code or some similar designation.</P>
            <P>(e)(1) All books and records required to be made under the provisions of paragraphs (a) to (c)(1)(i), inclusive, and (c)(2) of this section (except for books and records required to be made under the provisions of paragraphs (a)(11), (a)(12)(i), (a)(12)(iii), (a)(13)(ii), (a)(13)(iii), (a)(16), and (a)(17)(i) of this section), shall be maintained and preserved in an easily accessible place for a period of not less than five years from the end of the fiscal year during which the last entry was made on such record, the first two years in an appropriate office of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(2) Partnership articles and any amendments thereto, articles of incorporation, charters, minute books, and stock certificate books of the investment adviser and of any predecessor, shall be maintained in the principal office of the investment adviser and preserved until at least three years after termination of the enterprise.</P>
            <P>(3)(i) Books and records required to be made under the provisions of paragraphs (a)(11) and (a)(16) of this rule shall be maintained and preserved in an easily accessible place for a period of not less than five years, the first two years in an appropriate office of the investment adviser, from the end of the fiscal year during which the investment adviser last published or otherwise disseminated, directly or indirectly, the notice, circular, advertisement, newspaper article, investment letter, bulletin or other communication.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Transition rule.</E>(ii)If you are an investment adviser that was, prior to July 21, 2011, exempt from registration under section 203(b)(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)), as in effect on July 20, 2011, paragraph (e)(3)(i) of this section does not require you to maintain or preserve books and records that would otherwise be required to be maintained or preserved under the provisions of paragraph (a)(16) of this section to the extent those books and records pertain to the performance or rate of return of such private fund (as defined in section 202(a)(29) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(29)), or other account you advise for any period ended prior to your registration, provided that you continue to preserve any books and records in your possession that pertain to the performance or rate of return of such private fund or other account for such period.</P>
            <P>(f) An investment adviser subject to paragraph (a) of this section, before ceasing to conduct or discontinuing business as an investment adviser shall arrange for and be responsible for the preservation of the books and records required to be maintained and preserved under this section for the remainder of the period specified in this section, and shall notify the Commission in writing, at its principal office, Washington, D.C. 20549, of the exact address where such books and records will be maintained during such period.</P>
            <P>(g)<E T="03">Micrographic and electronic storage permitted</E>
                <E T="03">General.</E>—(1)The records required to be maintained and preserved pursuant to this part may be maintained and preserved for the required time by an investment adviser on:</P>
            <P>(i) Micrographic media, including microfilm, microfiche, or any similar medium; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Electronic storage media, including any digital storage medium or system that meets the terms of this section.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">General requirements.</E>The investment adviser must:</P>
            <P>(i) Arrange and index the records in a way that permits easy location, access, and retrieval of any particular record;</P>
            <P>(ii) Provide promptly any of the following that the Commission (by its examiners or other representatives) may request:</P>
            <P>(A) A legible, true, and complete copy of the record in the medium and format in which it is stored;</P>
            <P>(B) A legible, true, and complete printout of the record; and</P>
            <P>(C) Means to access, view, and print the records; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Separately store, for the time required for preservation of the original record, a duplicate copy of the record on any medium allowed by this section.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Special requirements for electronic storage media.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="957"/>In the case of records on electronic storage media, the investment adviser must establish and maintain procedures:</P>
            <P>(i) To maintain and preserve the records, so as to reasonably safeguard them from loss, alteration, or destruction;</P>
            <P>(ii) To limit access to the records to properly authorized personnel and the Commission (including its examiners and other representatives); and</P>
            <P>(iii) To reasonably ensure that any reproduction of a non-electronic original record on electronic storage media is complete, true, and legible when retrieved.</P>
            <P>(h)(1) Any book or other record made, kept, maintained and preserved in compliance with §§ 240.17a-3 and 240.17a-4 of this chapter under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, or with rules adopted by the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board, which is substantially the same as the book or other record required to be made, kept, maintained and preserved under this section, shall be deemed to be made, kept, maintained and preserved in compliance with this section.</P>
            <P>(2) A record made and kept pursuant to any provision of paragraph (a) of this section, which contains all the information required under any other provision of paragraph (a) of this section, need not be maintained in duplicate in order to meet the requirements of the other provision of paragraph (a) of this section.</P>
            <P>(i) As used in this section the term “discretionary power” shall not include discretion as to the price at which or the time when a transaction is or is to be effected, if, before the order is given by the investment adviser, the client has directed or approved the purchase or sale of a definite amount of the particular security.</P>
            <P>(j)(1) Except as provided in paragraph (j)(3) of this section, each non-resident investment adviser registered or applying for registration pursuant to section 203 of the Act shall keep, maintain and preserve, at a place within the United States designated in a notice from him as provided in paragraph (j)(2) of this section true, correct, complete and current copies of books and records which he is required to make, keep current, maintain or preserve pursuant to any provisions of any rule or regulation of the Commission adopted under the Act.</P>
            <P>(2) Except as provided in paragraph (j)(3) of this section, each nonresident investment adviser subject to this paragraph (j) shall furnish to the Commission a written notice specifying the address of the place within the United States where the copies of the books and records required to be kept and preserved by him pursuant to paragraph (j)(1) of this section are located. Each non-resident investment adviser registered or applying for registration when this paragraph becomes effective shall file such notice within 30 days after such rule becomes effective. Each non-resident investment adviser who files an application for registration after this paragraph becomes effective shall file such notice with such application for registration.</P>
            <P>(3) Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs (j)(1) and (2) of this section, a non-resident investment adviser need not keep or preserve within the United States copies of the books and records referred to in said paragraphs (j)(1) and (2), if:</P>
            <P>(i) Such non-resident investment adviser files with the Commission, at the time or within the period provided by paragraph (j)(2) of this section, a written undertaking, in form acceptable to the Commission and signed by a duly authorized person, to furnish to the Commission, upon demand, at its principal office in Washington, DC, or at any Regional Office of the Commission designated in such demand, true, correct, complete and current copies of any or all of the books and records which he is required to make, keep current, maintain or preserve pursuant to any provision of any rule or regulation of the Commission adopted under the Act, or any part of such books and records which may be specified in such demand. Such undertaking shall be in substantially the following form:</P>
            <EXTRACT>
                <P>
                    <PRTPAGE P="958"/>The undersigned hereby undertakes to furnish at its own expense to the Securities and Exchange Commission at its principal office in Washington, DC or at any Regional Office of said Commission specified in a demand for copies of books and records made by or on behalf of said Commission, true, correct, complete and current copies of any or all, or any part, of the books and records which the undersigned is required to make, keep current or preserve pursuant to any provision of any rule or regulation of the Securities andExchange Commission under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940. This undertaking shall be suspended during any period when the undersigned is making, keeping current, and preserving copies of all of said books and records at a place within the United States in compliance with Rule 204-2(j) under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940. This undertaking shall be binding upon the undersigned and the heirs, successors and assigns of the undersigned, and the written irrevocable consents and powers of attorney of the undersigned, its general partners and managing agents filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission shall extend to and cover any action to enforce same.</P>
            </EXTRACT>
            <FP>and</FP>
            <P>(ii) Such non-resident investment adviser furnishes to the Commission, at his own expense 14 days after written demand therefor forwarded to him by registered mail at his last address of record filed with the Commission and signed by the Secretary of the Commission or such person as the Commission may authorize to act in its behalf, true, correct, complete and current copies of any or all books and records which such investment adviser is required to make, keep current or preserve pursuant to any provision of any rule or regulation of the Commission adopted under the Act, or any part of such books and records which may be specified in said written demand. Such copies shall be furnished to the Commission at its principal office in Washington, DC, or at any Regional Office of the Commission which may be specified in said written demand.</P>
            <P>(4) For purposes of this rule the term<E T="03">non-resident investment adviser</E>shall have the meaning set out in § 275.0-2(d)(3) under the Act.</P>
            <P>(k) Every investment adviser that registers under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3) after July 8, 1997 shall be required to preserve in accordance with this section the books and records the investment adviser had been required to maintain by the State in which the investment adviser had its principal office and place of business prior to registering with the Commission.</P>
            <CITA>[26 FR 5002, June 6, 1961]</CITA>
            <EDNOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
                <P>For<E T="04">Federal Register</E>
                    <E T="03">www.fdsys.gov</E>citations affecting § 275.204-2, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at.</P>
            </EDNOTE>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Delivery of brochures and brochure supplements.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">General requirements.</E>(a)If you are registered under the Act as an investment adviser, you must deliver a brochure and one or more brochure supplements to each client or prospective client that contains all information required by Part 2 of Form ADV [17 CFR 279.1].</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Delivery requirements.</E>Subject to paragraph (g), you (or a supervised person acting on your behalf) must:</P>
            <P>(1) Deliver to a client or prospective client your current brochure before or at the time you enter into an investment advisory contract with that client.</P>
            <P>(2) Deliver to each client, annually within 120 days after the end of your fiscal year and without charge, if there are material changes in your brochure since your last annual updating amendment:</P>
            <P>(i) A current brochure, or</P>
            <P>(ii) The summary of material changes to the brochure as required by Item 2 of Form ADV, Part 2A that offers to provide your current brochure without charge, accompanied by the Web site address (if available) and an e-mail address (if available) and telephone number by which a client may obtain the current brochure from you, and the Web site address for obtaining information about you through the Investment Adviser Public Disclosure (IAPD) system.</P>

            <P>(3) Deliver to each client or prospective client a current brochure supplement for a supervised person before or at the time that supervised person begins to provide advisory services to the client; provided, however, that if investment advice for a client is provided by a team comprised of more than five supervised persons, a current brochure supplement need only be delivered to that client for the five supervised persons with the most significant responsibility for the day-to-day advice provided to that client. For purposes of this section, a supervised person will provide advisory services to a client if that supervised person will:<PRTPAGE P="959"/>
            </P>
            <P>(i) Formulate investment advice for the client and have direct client contact; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Make discretionary investment decisions for the client, even if the supervised person will have no direct client contact.</P>
            <P>(4) Deliver the following to each client promptly after you create an amended brochure or brochure supplement, as applicable, if the amendment adds disclosure of an event, or materially revises information already disclosed about an event, in response to Item 9 of Part 2A of Form ADV or Item 3 of Part 2B of Form ADV (Disciplinary Information), respectively, (i) the amended brochure or brochure supplement, as applicable, along with a statement describing the material facts relating to the change in disciplinary information, or (ii) a statement describing the material facts relating to the change in disciplinary information.</P>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">Exceptions to delivery requirement.</E>(1) You are not required to deliver a brochure to a client:</P>
            <P>(i) That is an investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 [15 U.S.C. 80a-1 to 80a-64] or a business development company as defined in that Act, provided that the advisory contract with that client meets the requirements of section 15(c) of that Act [15 U.S.C. 80a-15(c)]; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Who receives only impersonal investment advice for which you charge less than $500 per year.</P>
            <P>(2) You are not required to deliver a brochure supplement to a client:</P>
            <P>(i) To whom you are not required to deliver a brochure under subparagraph (c)(1) of this section;</P>
            <P>(ii) Who receives only impersonal investment advice; or</P>
            <P>(iii) Who is an officer, employee, or other person related to the adviser that would be a “qualified client” of your firm under § 275.205-3(d)(1)(iii).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Wrap fee program brochures.</E>(d)(1) If you are a sponsor of a wrap fee program, then the brochure that paragraph (b) of this section requires you to deliver to a client or prospective client of the wrap fee program must be a wrap fee program brochure containing all the information required by Part 2A, Appendix 1 of Form ADV. Any additional information in a wrap fee program brochure must be limited to information applicable to wrap fee programs that you sponsor.</P>
            <P>(2) You do not have to deliver a wrap fee program brochure if another sponsor of the wrap fee program delivers, to the client or prospective client of the wrap fee program, a wrap fee program brochure containing all the information required by Part 2A, Appendix 1 of Form ADV.</P>
            <P>Note to paragraph (d): A wrap fee program brochure does not take the place of any brochure supplements that you are required to deliver under paragraph (b) of this section.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Multiple brochures.</E>(e)If you provide substantially different advisory services to different clients, you may provide them with different brochures, so long as each client receives all information about the services and fees that are applicable to that client. The brochure you deliver to a client may omit any information required by Part 2A of Form ADV if the information does not apply to the advisory services or fees that you will provide or charge, or that you propose to provide or charge, to that client.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Other disclosure obligations.</E>(f)Delivering a brochure or brochure supplement in compliance with this section does not relieve you of any other disclosure obligations you have to your advisory clients or prospective clients under any federal or state laws or regulations.</P>
            <P>(g)<E T="03">Transition rule.</E>(1) Within 60 days after the date by which you are first required by § 275.204-1(c) to electronically file your brochure(s) with the Commission, you must deliver to each of your existing clients your current brochure and all current brochure supplements as required by Part 2 of Form ADV.</P>
            <P>(2) As of the date by which you are first required to electronically file your brochure(s) with the Commission, you must begin using your current brochure and current brochure supplements as required by Part 2 of Form ADV to comply with the requirements of this section pertaining to initial delivery to new and prospective clients.</P>
            <P>(h)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="960"/>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Impersonal investment advice</E>means investment advisory services that do not purport to meet the objectives or needs of specific individuals or accounts.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Current brochure</E>
                <E T="03">current brochure supplement</E>andmean the most recent revision of the brochure or brochure supplement, including all amendments to date.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Sponsor</E>(3)of a wrap fee program means an investment adviser that is compensated under a wrap fee program for sponsoring, organizing, or administering the program, or for selecting, or providing advice to clients regarding the selection of, other investment advisers in the program.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Supervised person</E>(4)means any of your officers, partners or directors (or other persons occupying a similar status or performing similar functions) or employees, or any other person who provides investment advice on your behalf.</P>
            <P>(5)<E T="03">Wrap fee program</E>means an advisory program under which a specified fee or fees not based directly upon transactions in a client's account is charged for investment advisory services (which may include portfolio management or advice concerning the selection of other investment advisers) and the execution of client transactions.</P>
            <CITA>[75 FR 49268, Aug. 12, 2010]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204-4</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Reporting by exempt reporting advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Exempt reporting advisers.</E>If you are an investment adviser relying on the exemption from registering with the Commission under section 203(l) or (m) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(l) or 80b-3(m)), you must complete and file reports on Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) by following the instructions in the Form, which specify the information that an exempt reporting adviser must provide.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Electronic filing.</E>You must file Form ADV electronically with the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD) unless you have received a hardship exemption under paragraph (e) of this section.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">b</E>Note to paragraph ():</HD>
                <P>
                    <E T="03">http://www.sec.gov/iard.</E>Information on how to file with the IARD is available on the Commission's Web site at</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>
                <E T="03">When filed.</E>(c)Each Form ADV is considered filed with the Commission upon acceptance by the IARD.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Filing fees.</E>(d)You must pay FINRA (the operator of the IARD) a filing fee. The Commission has approved the amount of the filing fee. No portion of the filing fee is refundable. Your completed Form ADV will not be accepted by FINRA, and thus will not be considered filed with the Commission, until you have paid the filing fee.</P>
            <P>(e)<E T="03">Temporary hardship exemption</E>
                <E T="03">Eligibility for exemption.</E>—(1)If you have unanticipated technical difficulties that prevent submission of a filing to the IARD, you may request a temporary hardship exemption from the requirements of this chapter to file electronically.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Application procedures.</E>To request a temporary hardship exemption, you must:</P>
            <P>(i) File Form ADV-H (17 CFR 279.3) in paper format no later than one business day after the filing that is the subject of the ADV-H was due; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Submit the filing that is the subject of the Form ADV-H in electronic format with the IARD no later than seven business days after the filing was due.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Effective date—upon filing.</E>The temporary hardship exemption will be granted when you file a completed Form ADV-H.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Final report.</E>(f)You must file a final report in accordance with instructions in Form ADV when:</P>
            <P>(1) You cease operation as an investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(2) You no longer meet the definition of exempt reporting adviser under paragraph (a); or</P>
            <P>(3) You apply for registration with the Commission.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">f</E>Note to paragraph ():</HD>
                <P>You do not have to pay a filing fee to file a final report on Form ADV through the IARD.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[76 FR 43013, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204(b)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Reporting by investment advisers to private funds.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Reporting by investment advisers to private funds on Form PF.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="961"/>If you are an investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), you act as an investment adviser to one ormore private funds and, as of the end of your most recently completed fiscal year, you managed private fund assets of at least $150 million, you must complete and file a report on Form PF (17 CFR 279.9) by following the instructions in the Form, which specify the information that an investment adviser must provide. Your initial report on Form PF is due no later than the last day on which your next update would be timely in accordance with paragraph (e) if you had previously filed the Form; provided that you are not required to file Form PF with respect to any fiscal quarter or fiscal year ending prior to the date on which your registration becomes effective.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Electronic filing.</E>(b)You must file Form PF electronically with the Form PF filing system on the Investment Adviser Registration Depository (IARD).</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">
                    <E T="01">b</E>Note to paragraph ():</HD>

                <P>Information on how to file Form PF is available on the Commission's Web site at<E T="03">http://www.sec.gov/iard.</E>
                </P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">When filed.</E>Each Form PF is considered filed with the Commission upon acceptance by the Form PF filing system.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Filing fees.</E>(d)You must pay the operator of the Form PF filing system a filing fee as required by the instructions to Form PF. The Commission has approved the amount of the filing fee. No portion of the filing fee is refundable. Your completed Form PF will not be accepted by the operator of the Form PF filing system, and thus will not be considered filed with the Commission, until you have paid the filing fee.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Updates to Form PF.</E>(e)You must file an updated Form PF:</P>
            <P>(1) At least annually, no later than the date specified in the instructions to Form PF; and</P>
            <P>(2) More frequently, if required by the instructions to Form PF. You must file all updated reports electronically with the Form PF filing system.</P>
            <P>(f)<E T="03">Temporary hardship exemption.</E>(1) If you have unanticipated technical difficulties that prevent you from submitting Form PF on a timely basis through the Form PF filing system, you may request a temporary hardship exemption from the requirements of this section to file electronically.</P>
            <P>(2) To request a temporary hardship exemption, you must:</P>
            <P>(i) Complete and file in paper format, in accordance with the instructions to Form PF, Item A of Section 1a and Section 5 of Form PF, checking the box in Section 1a indicating that you are requesting a temporary hardship exemption, no later than one business day after the electronic Form PF filing was due; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Submit the filing that is the subject of the Form PF paper filing in electronic format with the Form PF filing system no later than seven business days after the filing was due.</P>
            <P>(3) The temporary hardship exemption will be granted when you file Item A of Section 1a and Section 5 of Form PF, checking the box in Section 1a indicating that you are requesting a temporary hardship exemption.</P>
            <P>(4) The hardship exemptions available under § 275.203-3 do not apply to Form PF.</P>
            <P>(g)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Assets under management</E>means the regulatory assets under management as determined under Item 5.F of Form ADV (§ 279.1 of this chapter).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Private fund assets</E>(2)means the investment adviser's assets under management attributable to private funds.</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 71174, Nov. 16, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204A-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Investment adviser codes of ethics.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Adoption of code of ethics.</E>If you are an investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), you must establish, maintain and enforce a written code of ethics that, at a minimum, includes:</P>
            <P>(1) A standard (or standards) of business conduct that you require of your supervised persons, which standard must reflect your fiduciary obligations and those of your supervised persons;</P>
            <P>(2) Provisions requiring your supervised persons to comply with applicable Federal securities laws;</P>

            <P>(3) Provisions that require all of your access persons to report, and you to review, their personal securities transactions and holdings periodically as provided below;<PRTPAGE P="962"/>
            </P>
            <P>(4) Provisions requiring supervised persons to report any violations of your code of ethics promptly to your chief compliance officer or, provided your chief compliance officer also receives reports of all violations, to other persons you designate in your code of ethics; and</P>
            <P>(5) Provisions requiring you to provide each of your supervised persons with a copy of your code of ethics and any amendments, and requiring your supervised persons to provide you with a written acknowledgment of their receipt of the code and any amendments.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Reporting requirements</E>(b)—(1)<E T="03">Holdings reports.</E>The code of ethics must require your access persons to submit to your chief compliance officer or other persons you designate in your code of ethics a report of the access person's current securities holdings that meets the following requirements:</P>
            <P>(i)<E T="03">Content of holdings reports.</E>Each holdings report must contain, at a minimum:</P>
            <P>(A) The title and type of security, and as applicable the exchange ticker symbol or CUSIP number, number of shares, and principal amount of each reportable security in which the access person has any direct or indirect beneficial ownership;</P>
            <P>(B) The name of any broker, dealer or bank with which the access person maintains an account in which any securities are held for the access person's direct or indirect benefit; and</P>
            <P>(C) The date the access person submits the report.</P>
            <P>(ii)<E T="03">Timing of holdings reports.</E>Your access persons must each submit a holdings report:</P>
            <P>(A) No later than 10 days after the person becomes an access person, and the information must be current as of a date no more than 45 days prior to the date the person becomes an access person.</P>
            <P>(B) At least once each 12-month period thereafter on a date you select, and the information must be current as of a date no more than 45 days prior to the date the report was submitted.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Transaction reports.</E>The code of ethics must require access persons to submit to your chief compliance officer or other persons you designate in your code of ethics quarterly securities transactions reports that meet the following requirements:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Content of transaction reports.</E>(i)Each transaction report must contain, at a minimum, the following information about each transaction involving a reportable security in which the access person had, or as a result of the transaction acquired, any direct or indirect beneficial ownership:</P>
            <P>(A) The date of the transaction, the title, and as applicable the exchange ticker symbol or CUSIP number, interest rate and maturity date, number of shares, and principal amount of each reportable security involved;</P>
            <P>(B) The nature of the transaction (i.e., purchase, sale or any other type of acquisition or disposition);</P>
            <P>(C) The price of the security at which the transaction was effected;</P>
            <P>(D) The name of the broker, dealer or bank with or through which the transaction was effected; and</P>
            <P>(E) The date the access person submits the report.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Timing of transaction reports.</E>(ii)Each access person must submit a transaction report no later than 30 days after the end of each calendar quarter, which report must cover, at a minimum, all transactions during the quarter.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Exceptions from reporting requirements.</E>(3)Your code of ethics need not require an access person to submit:</P>
            <P>(i) Any report with respect to securities held in accounts over which the access person had no direct or indirect influence or control;</P>
            <P>(ii) A transaction report with respect to transactions effected pursuant to an automatic investment plan;</P>
            <P>(iii) A transaction report if the report would duplicate information contained in broker trade confirmations or account statements that you hold in your records so long as you receive the confirmations or statements no later than 30 days after the end of the applicable calendar quarter.</P>
            <P>(c)<E
                    T="03">Pre-approval of certain investments.</E>Your code of ethics must require your access persons to obtain your approval before they directly or indirectly acquire beneficial ownership in any security in an initial public offering or in a limited offering.<PRTPAGE P="963"/>
            </P>
            <P>(d)<E T="03">Small advisers.</E>If you have only one access person (i.e., yourself), you are not required to submit reports to yourself or to obtain your own approval for investments in any security in an initial public offering or in a limited offering, if you maintain records of all of your holdings and transactions that this section would otherwise require you to report.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definitions.</E>(e)For the purpose of this section:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Access person</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) Any of your supervised persons:</P>
            <P>(A) Who has access to nonpublic information regarding any clients' purchase or sale of securities, or nonpublic information regarding the portfolio holdings of any reportable fund, or</P>
            <P>(B) Who is involved in making securities recommendations to clients, or who has access to such recommendations that are nonpublic.</P>
            <P>(ii) If providing investment advice is your primary business, all of your directors, officers and partners are presumed to be access persons.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Automatic investment plan</E>(2)means a program in which regular periodic purchases (or withdrawals) are made automatically in (or from) investment accounts in accordance with a predetermined schedule and allocation. An automatic investment plan includes a dividend reinvestment plan.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Beneficial ownership</E>is interpreted in the same manner as it would be under § 240.16a-1(a)(2) of this chapter in determining whether a person has beneficial ownership of a security for purposes of section 16 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78p) and the rules and regulations thereunder. Any report required by paragraph (b) of this section may contain a statement that the report will not be construed as an admission that the person making the report has any direct or indirect beneficial ownership in the security to which the report relates.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Federal securities laws</E>(4)means the Securities Act of 1933 (15 U.S.C. 77a-aa), the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78a-mm), the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002 (Pub. L. 107-204, 116 Stat. 745 (2002)), the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a), the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80b), title V of the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act (Pub. L. 106-102, 113 Stat. 1338 (1999), any rules adopted by the Commission under any of these statutes, the Bank Secrecy Act (31 U.S.C. 5311-5314; 5316-5332) as it applies to funds and investment advisers, and any rules adopted thereunder by the Commission or the Department of the Treasury.</P>
            <P>(5)<E T="03">Fund</E>means an investment company registered under the Investment Company Act.</P>
            <P>(6)<E T="03">Initial public offering</E>means an offering of securities registered under the Securities Act of 1933 (15 U.S.C. 77a), the issuer of which, immediately before the registration, was not subject to the reporting requirements of sections 13 or 15(d) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78m or 78o(d)).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Limited offering</E>(7)means an offering that is exempt from registration under the Securities Act of 1933 pursuant to section 4(2) or section 4(5) (15 U.S.C. 77d(2) or 77d(5)) or pursuant to §§ 230.504, 230.505, or 230.506 of this chapter.</P>
            <P>(8)<E T="03">Purchase or sale of a security</E>includes, among other things, the writing of an option to purchase or sell a security.</P>
            <P>(9)<E T="03">Reportable fund</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) Any fund for which you serve as an investment adviser as defined in section 2(a)(20) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(20)) (i.e., in most cases you must be approved by the fund's board of directors before you can serve); or</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">control</E>(ii) Any fund whose investment adviser or principal underwriter controls you, is controlled by you, or is under common control with you. For purposes of this section,has the same meaning as it does in section 2(a)(9) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(9)).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Reportable security</E>(10)means a security as defined in section 202(a)(18) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(18)), except that it does not include:</P>
            <P>(i) Direct obligations of the Government of the United States;</P>
            <P>(ii) Bankers' acceptances, bank certificates of deposit, commercial paper and high quality short-term debt instruments, including repurchase agreements;</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="964"/>(iii) Shares issued by money market funds;</P>
            <P>(iv) Shares issued by open-end funds other than reportable funds; and</P>
            <P>(v) Shares issued by unit investment trusts that are invested exclusively in one or more open-end funds, none of which are reportable funds.</P>
            <CITA>[69 FR 41708, July 9, 2004, as amended at 76 FR 81806, Dec. 29, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.204-5</SECTNO>
            <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.205-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “investment performance” of an investment company and “investment record” of an appropriate index of securities prices.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Investment performance</E>of an investment company for any period shall mean the sum of:</P>
            <P>(1) The change in its net asset value per share during such period;</P>
            <P>(2) The value of its cash distributions per share accumulated to the end of such period; and</P>
            <P>(3) The value of capital gains taxes per share paid or payable on undistributed realized long-term capital gains accumulated to the end of such period; expressed as a percentage of its net asset value per share at the beginning of such period. For this purpose, the value of distributions per share of realized capital gains, of dividends per share paid from investment income and of capital gains taxes per share paid or payable on undistributed realized long-term capital gains shall be treated as reinvested in shares of the investment company at the net asset value per share in effect at the close of business on the record date for the payment of such distributions and dividends and the date on which provision is made for such taxes, after giving effect to such distributions, dividends and taxes.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Investment record</E>of an appropriate index of securities prices for any period shall mean the sum of:</P>
            <P>(1) The change in the level of the index during such period; and</P>
            <P>(2) The value, computed consistently with the index, of cash distributions made by companies whose securities comprise the index accumulated to the end of such period; expressed as a percentage of the index level at the beginning of such period. For this purpose cash distributions on the securities which comprise the index shall be treated as reinvested in the index at least as frequently as the end of each calendar quarter following the payment of the dividend.</P>
            <GPOTABLE CDEF="s100,10,10,10" COLS="4" OPTS="L2">
                <TTITLE>Exhibit I</TTITLE>
                <TDESC>[<E T="04">Method of computing the investment record of the standard</E>
                    <E T="04">poor's</E>&amp;500<E T="04">stock composite index for calendar</E>1971]</TDESC>
                <BOXHD>
                    <CHED H="1">Quarterly ending—</CHED>
                    <CHED H="1">
                        <SU>1</SU>Index value</CHED>
                    <CHED H="1">Quarterly dividend yield-composite index</CHED>
                    <CHED H="2">
                        <SU>2</SU>Annual percent</CHED>
                    <CHED H="2">
                        <SU>3</SU>Quarterly percent(<FR>1/4</FR>of annual)</CHED>
                </BOXHD>
                <ROW>
                    <ENT I="01">Dec. 1970</ENT>
                    <ENT>92.15</ENT>
                    <ENT/>
                    <ENT/>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                    <ENT I="01">Mar. 1971</ENT>
                    <ENT>100.31</ENT>
                    <ENT>3.10</ENT>
                    <ENT>0.78</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                    <ENT I="01">June 1971</ENT>
                    <ENT>99.70</ENT>
                    <ENT>3.11</ENT>
                    <ENT>.78</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                    <ENT I="01">Sept. 1971</ENT>
                    <ENT>98.34</ENT>
                    <ENT>3.14</ENT>
                    <ENT>.79</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <ROW>
                    <ENT I="01">Dec. 1971</ENT>
                    <ENT>102.09</ENT>
                    <ENT>3.01</ENT>
                    <ENT>.75</ENT>
                </ROW>
                <TNOTE>
                    <SU>1</SU>Source: Standard &amp; Poor's Trade and Securities Statistics, Jan. 1972, p. 33.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>
                    <SU>2</SU>
                    <E T="03">Id.</E>See Standard &amp; Poor's Trade and Securities Statistics Security and Price Index Record—1970 Edition, p. 133 for explanation of quarterly dividend yield.</TNOTE>
                <TNOTE>
                    <SU>3</SU>Quarterly percentages have been founded to two decimal places.</TNOTE>
            </GPOTABLE>
            <EXTRACT>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Change in index value for 1971: 102.09-92.15=9.94.</FP>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Accumulated value of dividends for 1971:</FP>
                <MATH DEEP="26" SPAN="2">
                    <MID>EC14NO91.094</MID>
                </MATH>
                <PRTPAGE P="965"/>
                <P>Aggregate value of dividends paid, assuming quarterly reinvestment and computed consistently with the index:</P>
                <P>(Percent yield as computed above) × (ending index value)=Aggregate value of dividends paid</P>
                <P>For 1971:</P>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">.0314×102.09=3.21</FP>
                <P>Investment record of Standard &amp; Poor's 500 stock composite index assuming quarterly reinvestment dividends:</P>
                <MATH DEEP="24" SPAN="1">
                    <MID>EC14NO91.095</MID>
                </MATH>
                <P>The same method can be extended to cases where an investment company's fiscal quarters do not coincide with the fiscal quarters of the S &amp; P dividend record or to instances where a “rolling period” is used for performance comparisons as indicated by the following example of the calculation of the investment record of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 Stock Composite Index for the 12 months ended November 1971:</P>
                <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,7" COLS="2" OPTS="L0">
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Index value Nov. 30, 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>93.99</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW RUL="n,s">
                        <ENT I="01">Index value Nov. 30, 1970</ENT>
                        <ENT>87.20</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Change in index value</ENT>
                        <ENT>6.79</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                </GPOTABLE>
                <GPOTABLE CDEF="s25,7,7,9" COLS="4" OPTS="L2">
                    <BOXHD>
                        <CHED H="1">Quarter ending—</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">Dividend yield</CHED>
                        <CHED H="2">Annual rate</CHED>
                        <CHED H="2">
                            <FR>1/4</FR>of annual</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">
                            <FR>1/12</FR>Rate for each month of quarter (of annual)</CHED>
                    </BOXHD>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1970</ENT>
                        <ENT>3.41</ENT>
                        <ENT>0.85</ENT>
                        <ENT>0.28</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Mar. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>3.10</ENT>
                        <ENT>.78</ENT>
                        <ENT>.26</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">June 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>3.11</ENT>
                        <ENT>.78</ENT>
                        <ENT>.26</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Sept. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>3.14</ENT>
                        <ENT>.79</ENT>
                        <ENT>.26</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>3.01</ENT>
                        <ENT>.75</ENT>
                        <ENT>.25</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                </GPOTABLE>
                <P>Accumulated value of dividends reinvested:</P>
                <P>December=1.0028</P>
                <P>January-March=1.0078</P>
                <P>April-June=1.0078</P>
                <P>July-September=1.0079</P>
                <P>
                    <SU>4</SU>October-November=1.0053<FTREF/>
                </P>
                <FTNT>
                    <P>
                        <SU>4</SU>The rate for October and November would be two-thirds of the yield for the quarter ended Sept. 30 (i.e. .667×.79=5269) since the yield for the quarter ended Dec. 31 would not be available as of Nov. 30.</P>
                </FTNT>
                <P>Dividend yield:</P>
                <HD SOURCE="HD1">(1.0028×1.0078×1.0078×1.0079× 1.0053)−1.00=.0320</HD>
                <P>Aggregate value of dividends paid computed consistently with the index:</P>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">.0320×93.99=3.01</FP>
                <P>Investment record of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 Stock Composite Index for the 12 months ended November 30, 1971:</P>
                <MATH DEEP="24" SPAN="1">
                    <MID>EC14NO91.096</MID>
                </MATH>
                <GPOTABLE CDEF="s100,10,10,10,10" COLS="5" OPTS="L2">
                    <TTITLE>Exhibit II</TTITLE>
                    <TDESC>
                        <E T="04">Method of Computing the Investment Record of the New York Stock Exchange Composite Index for Calendar</E>[1971]</TDESC>
                    <BOXHD>
                        <CHED H="1">(1)—Quarter ending</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">(2)—Index value<SU>1</SU>
                        </CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">
                            <SU>2</SU>(3)—Aggregate market value of shares listed on the NYSE as of end of quarter (billions of dollars)</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">
                            <SU>3</SU>(4)—Quarterly value of estimated cash payments of shares listed on the NYSE (millions of dollars)</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">
                            <SU>4</SU>(5)—Estimated yield(quarterly percent)</CHED>
                    </BOXHD>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1970</ENT>
                        <ENT>50.23</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Mar. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>55.44</ENT>
                        <ENT>$709</ENT>
                        <ENT>$5,106</ENT>
                        <ENT>0.72</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">June 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>55.09</ENT>
                        <ENT>710</ENT>
                        <ENT>4,961</ENT>
                        <ENT>.70</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Sept. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>54.33</ENT>
                        <ENT>709</ENT>
                        <ENT>5,006</ENT>
                        <ENT>.71</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>56.43</ENT>
                        <ENT>742</ENT>
                        <ENT>5,183</ENT>
                        <ENT>.70</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <TNOTE>
                        <SU>1</SU>Source: New York Stock Exchange Composite Index as reported daily by the New York Stock Exchange.</TNOTE>
                    <TNOTE>
                        <SU>2</SU>Source: Monthly Review, New York Stock Exchange.</TNOTE>
                    <TNOTE>
                        <SU>3</SU>Source: The Exchange, New York Stock Exchange magazine, May, Aug., Nov. 1971 and Feb. 1972 editions. Upon request the Statistics Division of the Research Department of the NYSE will make this figure available within 10 days of the end of each quarter.</TNOTE>
                    <TNOTE>
                        <SU>4</SU>The ratio of column 4 to column 3.</TNOTE>
                </GPOTABLE>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Change in NYSE Composite Index value for 1971: 56.43−50.23=6.20.</FP>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">Accumulated Value of Dividends of NYSE Composite Index for 1971:</FP>
                <MATH DEEP="26" SPAN="2">
                    <PRTPAGE P="966"/>
                    <MID>EC14NO91.097</MID>
                </MATH>
                <P>Aggregate value of dividends paid on NYSE Composite Index assuming quarterly reinvestment:</P>
                <P>For 1971:</P>
                <FP SOURCE="FP-1">.0286×56.43=1.61</FP>
                <P>Investment record of the New York Stock Exchange Composite Index assuming quarterly reinvestment of dividends:</P>
                <MATH DEEP="24" SPAN="1">
                    <MID>EC14NO91.098</MID>
                </MATH>
                <P>The same method can be extended to cases where an investment company's fiscal quarters do not coincide with the fiscal quarters of the NYSE dividend record or to instances where a “rolling period” is used for performance comparisons as indicated by the following example of the calculation of the investment record of the NYSE Composite Index for the 12 months ended November 1971:</P>
                <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,7" COLS="2" OPTS="L0,6/7">
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Index value Nov. 30, 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>51.84</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW RUL="n,s">
                        <ENT I="01">Index value Nov. 30, 1970</ENT>
                        <ENT>47.41</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Change in index value</ENT>
                        <ENT>4.43</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                </GPOTABLE>
                <GPOTABLE CDEF="s50,9,9" COLS="3" OPTS="L2">
                    <BOXHD>
                        <CHED H="1">Quarter ending</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">Dividend yield quarterly percent</CHED>
                        <CHED H="1">
                            <FR>1/12</FR>Rate for each month of quarter (of annual)</CHED>
                    </BOXHD>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1970</ENT>
                        <ENT>0.79</ENT>
                        <ENT>0.26</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Mar. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>.72</ENT>
                        <ENT>.24</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">June 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>.70</ENT>
                        <ENT>.23</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Sept. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>.71</ENT>
                        <ENT>.24</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                    <ROW>
                        <ENT I="01">Dec. 1971</ENT>
                        <ENT>.70</ENT>
                        <ENT>.23</ENT>
                    </ROW>
                </GPOTABLE>
                <P>Accumulated value of dividends reinvested:</P>
                <P>December=1.0026</P>
                <P>January-March=1.0072</P>
                <P>April-June=1.0070</P>
                <P>July-September=1.0071</P>
                <P>
                    <SU>4</SU>October-November=1.0047<FTREF/>
                </P>
                <FTNT>
                    <P>
                        <SU>4</SU>The rate for October and November would be two thirds of the yield for the quarter ended September 30 (i.e. .667×.71=4736), since the yield for the quarter ended December 31 would not be available as of November 30.</P>
                </FTNT>
                <P>Dividend yield:</P>
                <HD SOURCE="HD1">(1.0026×1.0072×1.0070×1.0071× 1.0047)−1.00=.0289</HD>
                <P>Aggregate value of dividends paid computed consistently with the index:</P>
            </EXTRACT>
            <FP SOURCE="FP-1">.0289×51.84=1.50</FP>
            <EXTRACT>
                <P>Investment record of the NYSE Composite Index for the 12 months ended November 30, 1971:</P>
            </EXTRACT>
            <MATH DEEP="24" SPAN="1">
                <MID>EC14NO91.099</MID>
            </MATH>
            <SECAUTH>(Secs. 205, 211, 54 Stat. 852, 74 Stat. 887, 15 U.S.C. 80b-205, 80b-211; sec. 25, 84 Stat. 1432, 1433, Pub. L. 91-547)</SECAUTH>
            <CITA>[37 FR 17468, Aug. 29, 1972]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.205-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “specified period” over which the asset value of the company or fund under management is averaged.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) For purposes of this rule:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Fulcrum fee</E>shall mean the fee which is paid or earned when the investment company's performance is equivalent to that of the index or other measure of performance.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Rolling period</E>(2)shall mean a period consisting of a specified number of subperiods of definite length in which the most recent subperiod is substituted for the earliest subperiod as time passes.</P>
            <P>(b) The specified period over which the asset value of the company or fund under management is averaged shall mean the period over which the investment performance of the company or fund and the investment record of an appropriate index of securities prices or such other measure of investment performance are computed.</P>
            <P>(c) Notwithstanding paragraph (b) of this section, the specified period over which the asset value of the company or fund is averaged for the purpose of computing the fulcrum fee may differ from the period over which the asset value is averaged for computing the performance related portion of the fee, only if:</P>
            <P>(1) The performance related portion of the fee is computed over a rolling period and the total fee is payable at the end of each subperiod of the rolling period; and</P>

            <P>(2) The fulcrum fee is computed on the basis of the asset value averaged<PRTPAGE P="967"/>over the most recent subperiod or subperiods of the rolling period.</P>
            <SECAUTH>(Secs. 205, 106A, 211; 54 Stat. 852, 855; 84 Stat. 1433, 15 U.S.C. 80b-5, 80b-6a, 80b-11)</SECAUTH>
            <CITA>[37 FR 24896, Nov. 22, 1972]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.205-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemption from the compensation prohibition of section 205(a)(1) for investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">General.</E>(a)<E T="03">Provided,</E>The provisions of section 205(a)(1) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-5(a)(1)) will not be deemed to prohibit an investment adviser from entering into, performing, renewing or extending an investment advisory contract that provides for compensation to the investment adviser on the basis of a share of the capital gains upon, or the capital appreciation of, the funds, or any portion of the funds, of a client,That the client entering into the contract subject to this section is a qualified client, as defined in paragraph (d)(1) of this section.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Identification of the client.</E>In the case of a private investment company, as defined in paragraph (d)(3) of this section, an investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940, or a business development company, as defined in section 202(a)(22) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(22)), each equity owner of any such company (except for the investment adviser entering into the contract and any other equity owners not charged a fee on the basis of a share of capital gains or capital appreciation) will be considered a client for purposes of paragraph (a) of this section.</P>
            <P>(c)<E T="03">Transition rule.</E>
                <E T="03">Provided,</E>(1) An investment adviser that entered into a contract before August 20, 1998 and satisfied the conditions of this section as in effect on the date that the contract was entered into will be considered to satisfy the conditions of this section;however, that this section will apply with respect to any natural person or company who is not a party to the contract prior to and becomes a party to the contract after August 20, 1998.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Advisers to private funds with non-qualified investors.</E>(2)If you are an investment adviser to a private investment company that is a private fund as that term is defined in § 275.203(b)(3)-1, and you were exempt from registration under section 203(b)(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)) prior to February 10, 2005, paragraph (b) of this section will not apply to the existing account of any equity owner of a private investment company who was an equity owner of that company prior to February 10, 2005.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Advisers to private funds with non-qualified clients.</E>(3)If you are an investment adviser to a private investment company that is a private fund as that term is defined in § 275.203(b)(3)-1, and you were exempt from registration under section 203(b)(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)) prior to February 10, 2005, section 205(a)(1) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-5(a)(1)) will not apply to any investment advisory contract you entered into prior to February 10, 2005, provided, however, that this paragraph will not apply with respect to any contract to which a private investment company is a party, and provided further that section 205(a)(1) of the Act will apply with respect to any natural person or company who is not a party to the contract prior to and becomes a party to the contract on or after February 10, 2005.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definitions.</E>(d)For the purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>(1) The term<E T="03">qualified client</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) A natural person who or a company that immediately after entering into the contract has at least $750,000 under the management of the investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(ii) A natural person who or a company that the investment adviser entering into the contract (and any person acting on his behalf) reasonably believes, immediately prior to entering into the contract, either:</P>
            <P>(A) Has a net worth (together, in the case of a natural person, with assets held jointly with a spouse) of more than $1,500,000 at the time the contract is entered into; or</P>
            <P>(B) Is a qualified purchaser as defined in section 2(a)(51)(A) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(51)(A)) at the time the contract is entered into; or</P>
            <P>(iii) A natural person who immediately prior to entering into the contract is:</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="968"/>(A) An executive officer, director, trustee, general partner, or personserving in a similar capacity, of the investment adviser; or</P>
            <P>(B) An employee of the investment adviser (other than an employee performing solely clerical, secretarial or administrative functions with regard to the investment adviser) who, in connection with his or her regular functions or duties, participates in the investment activities of such investment adviser, provided that such employee has been performing such functions and duties for or on behalf of the investment adviser, or substantially similar functions or duties for or on behalf of another company for at least 12 months.</P>
            <P>(2) The term<E T="03">company</E>has the same meaning as in section 202(a)(5) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(5)), but does not include a company that is required to be registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 but is not registered.</P>
            <P>(3) The term<E T="03">private investment company</E>means a company that would be defined as an investment company under section 3(a) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(a)) but for the exception provided from that definition by section 3(c)(1) of such Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(1)).</P>
            <P>(4) The term<E T="03">executive officer</E>means the president, any vice president in charge of a principal business unit, division or function (such as sales, administration or finance), any other officer who performs a policy-making function, or any other person who performs similar policy-making functions, for the investment adviser.</P>
            <CITA>[63 FR 39027, July 21, 1998, as amended at 69 FR 72088, Dec. 10, 2004]</CITA>
            <EFFDNOTP>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Effective Date Note:</HD>
                <P>At 77 FR 10368, Feb. 22, 2012, § 275.205-3 was amended by revising paragraphs (c), (d)(1)(i) and (ii), and adding paragraph (e) effective May 22, 2012. For the convenience of the user, the added and revised text is set forth as follows:</P>
                <REVTXT>
                    <SECTION>
                        <SECTNO>§ 275.205-3</SECTNO>
                        <SUBJECT>Exemption from the compensation prohibition of section 205(a)(1) for investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
                        <STARS/>
                        <P>(c)<E T="03">Transition rules</E>
                            <E
                                T="03">Registered investment advisers.</E>—(1)If a registered investment adviser entered into a contract and satisfied the conditions of this section that were in effect when the contract was entered into, the adviser will be considered to satisfy the conditions of this section;<E T="03">Provided,</E>however, that if a natural person or company who was not a party to the contract becomes a party (including an equity owner of a private investment company advised by the adviser), the conditions of this section in effect at that time will apply with regard to that person or company.</P>
                        <P>(2)<E
                                T="03">Registered investment advisers that were previously not registered.</E>If an investment adviser was not required to register with the Commission pursuant to section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3) and was not registered, section 205(a)(1) of the Act will not apply to an advisory contract entered into when the adviser was not required to register and was not registered, or to an account of an equity owner of a private investment company advised by the adviser if the account was established when the adviser was not required to register and was not registered;<E T="03">Provided,</E>however, that section 205(a)(1) of the Act will apply with regard to a natural person or company who was not a party to the contract and becomes a party (including an equity owner of a private investment company advised by the adviser) when the adviser is required to register.</P>
                        <P>
                            <E T="03">Certain transfers of interests.</E>(3)Solely for purposes of paragraphs (c)(1) and (c)(2) of this section, a transfer of an equity ownership interest in a private investment company by gift or bequest, or pursuant to an agreement related to a legal separation or divorce, will not cause the transferee to “become a party” to the contract and will not cause section 205(a)(1) of the Act to apply to such transferee.</P>
                        <P>(d) * * *</P>
                        <P>(1) * * *</P>
                        <P>(i) A natural person who, or a company that, immediately after entering into the contract has at least $1,000,000 under the management of the investment adviser;</P>
                        <P>(ii) A natural person who, or a company that, the investment adviser entering into the contract (and any person acting on his behalf) reasonably believes, immediately prior to entering into the contract, either:</P>
                        <P>(A) Has a net worth (together, in the case of a natural person, with assets held jointly with a spouse) of more than $2,000,000. For purposes of calculating a natural person's net worth:</P>
                        <P>(<E T="03">1</E>) The person's primary residence must not be included as an asset;</P>
                        <P>(<E T="03">2</E>
                            <PRTPAGE P="969"/>) Indebtedness secured by the person's primary residence, up to the estimated fair market value of the primary residence at the time the investment advisory contract is entered into may not be included as a liability (except that if the amount of such indebtedness outstanding at the time of calculation exceeds the amount outstanding 60 days before such time, other than as a result of the acquisition of the primary residence, theamount of such excess must be included as a liability); and</P>
                        <P>(<E T="03">3</E>) Indebtedness that is secured by the person's primary residence in excess of the estimated fair market value of the residence must be included as a liability; or</P>
                        <P>
                            <STARS/>(B) Is a qualified purchaser as defined in section 2(a)(51)(A) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-2(a)(51)(A)) at the time the contract is entered into; or</P>
                        <P>
                            <E T="03">Inflation adjustments.</E>(e)Pursuant to section 205(e) of the Act, the dollar amounts specified in paragraphs (d)(1)(i) and (d)(1)(ii)(A) of this section shall be adjusted by order of the Commission, on or about May 1, 2016 and issued approximately every five years thereafter. The adjusted dollar amounts established in such orders shall be computed by:</P>
                        <P>(1) Dividing the year-end value of the Personal Consumption Expenditures Chain-Type Price Index (or any successor index thereto), as published by the United States Department of Commerce, for the calendar year preceding the calendar year in which the order is being issued, by the year-end value of such index (or successor) for the calendar year 1997;</P>
                        <P>(2) For the dollar amount in paragraph (d)(1)(i) of this section, multiplying $750,000 times the quotient obtained in paragraph (e)(1) of this section and rounding the product to the nearest multiple of $100,000; and</P>
                        <P>(3) For the dollar amount in paragraph (d)(1)(ii)(A) of this section, multiplying $1,500,000 times the quotient obtained in paragraph (e)(1) of this section and rounding the product to the nearest multiple of $100,000.</P>
                    </SECTION>
                </REVTXT>
            </EFFDNOTP>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(3)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Exemption of investment advisers registered as broker-dealers in connection with the provision of certain investment advisory services.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Provided, however,</E>(a) An investment adviser which is a broker or dealer registered pursuant to section 15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 shall be exempt from section 206(3) in connection with any transaction in relation to which such broker or dealer is acting as an investment adviser solely (1) by means of publicly distributed written materials or publicly made oral statements; (2) by means of written materials or oral statements which do not purport to meet the objectives or needs of specific individuals or accounts; (3) through the issuance of statistical information containing no expressions of opinion as to the investment merits of a particular security; or (4) any combination of the foregoing services:That such materials and oral statements include a statement that if the purchaser of the advisory communication uses the services of the adviser in connection with a sale or purchase of a security which is a subject of such communication, the adviser may act as principal for its own account or as agent for another person.</P>
            <P>(b) For the purpose of this Rule, publicly distributed written materials are those which are distributed to 35 or more persons who pay for such materials, and publicly made oral statements are those made simultaneously to 35 or more persons who pay for access to such statements.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
                <P>The requirement that the investment adviser disclose that it may act as principal or agent for another person in the sale or purchase of a security that is the subject of investment advice does not relieve the investment adviser of any disclosure obligation which, depending upon the nature of the relationship between the investment adviser and the client, may be imposed by subparagraphs (1) or (2) of section 206 or the other provisions of the federal securities laws.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <CITA>[40 FR 38159, Aug. 27, 1975]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(3)-3T</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Temporary rule for principal trades with certain advisory clients.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) An investment adviser shall be deemed in compliance with the provisions of section 206(3) of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(3)) when the adviser directly or indirectly, acting as principal for its own account, sells to or purchases from an advisory client any security if:</P>
            <P>(1) The investment adviser exercises no “investment discretion” (as such term is defined in section 3(a)(35) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (“Exchange Act”) (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(35))), except investment discretion granted by the advisory client on a temporary or limited basis, with respect to the client's account;</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE
                    P="970"/>(2) Neither the investment adviser nor any person controlling, controlled by, or under common control with the investment adviser is the issuer of, or, at the time of the sale, an underwriter (as defined in section 202(a)(20) of the<E T="03">except that</E>Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(20))) of, the security;the investment adviser or a person controlling, controlled by, or under common control with the investment adviser may be an underwriter of an investment grade debt security (as defined in paragraph (c) of this section);</P>
            <P>(3) The advisory client has executed a written, revocable consent prospectively authorizing the investment adviser directly or indirectly to act as principal for its own account in selling any security to or purchasing any security from the advisory client, so long as such written consent is obtained after written disclosure to the advisory client explaining:</P>
            <P>(i) The circumstances under which the investment adviser directly or indirectly may engage in principal transactions;</P>
            <P>(ii) The nature and significance of conflicts with its client's interests as a result of the transactions; and</P>
            <P>(iii) How the investment adviser addresses those conflicts;</P>
            <P>(4) The investment adviser, prior to the execution of each principal transaction:</P>
            <P>(i) Informs the advisory client, orally or in writing, of the capacity in which it may act with respect to such transaction; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Obtains consent from the advisory client, orally or in writing, to act as principal for its own account with respect to such transaction;</P>
            <P>(5) The investment adviser sends a written confirmation at or before completion of each such transaction that includes, in addition to the information required by 17 CFR 240.10b-10, a conspicuous, plain English statement informing the advisory client that the investment adviser:</P>
            <P>(i) Disclosed to the client prior to the execution of the transaction that the adviser may be acting in a principal capacity in connection with the transaction and the client authorized the transaction; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Sold the security to, or bought the security from, the client for its own account;</P>
            <P>(6) The investment adviser sends to the client, no less frequently than annually, written disclosure containing a list of all transactions that were executed in the client's account in reliance upon this section, and the date and price of such transactions;</P>
            <P>(7) The investment adviser is a broker-dealer registered under section 15 of the Exchange Act (15 U.S.C. 78o) and each account for which the investment adviser relies on this section is a brokerage account subject to the Exchange Act, and the rules thereunder, and the rules of the self-regulatory organization(s) of which it is a member; and</P>
            <P>(8) Each written disclosure required by this section includes a conspicuous, plain English statement that the client may revoke the written consent referred to in paragraph (a)(3) of this section without penalty at any time by written notice to the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(b) This section shall not be construed as relieving in any way an investment adviser from acting in the best interests of an advisory client, including fulfilling the duty with respect to the best price and execution for the particular transaction for the advisory client; nor shall it relieve such person or persons from any obligation that may be imposed by sections 206(1) or (2) of the Advisers Act or by other applicable provisions of the federal securities laws.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">investment grade debt security</E>(c) For purposes of paragraph (a)(2) of this section, anmeans a non-convertible debt security that, at the time of sale, is rated in one of the four highest rating categories of at least two nationally recognized statistical rating organizations (as defined in section 3(a)(62) of the Exchange Act (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(62))).</P>
            <P>(d) This section will expire and no longer be effective on December 31, 2012.</P>
            <CITA>[72 FR 55042, Sept. 28, 2007, as amended at 74 FR 69015, Dec. 30, 2009]</CITA>
            <EFFDNOT>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Effective Date Note:</HD>
                <P>At 72 FR 55042, Sept. 28, 2007, § 275.206(3)-3T was added effective Sept. 30, 2007 through Dec. 31, 2009. At 75 FR 742, Jan. 6, 2010 the effective date was extended until Dec. 31, 2010. At 75 FR 82241, Dec. 30, 2010, the effective date was extended until December 31, 2012.</P>
            </EFFDNOT>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <PRTPAGE P="971"/>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(3)-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Agency cross transactions for advisory clients.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) An investment adviser, or a person registered as a broker-dealer under section 15 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78o) and controlling, controlled by, or under common control with an investment adviser, shall be deemed in compliance with the provisions of sections 206(3) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(3)) in effecting an agency cross transaction for an advisory client, if:</P>
            <P>(1) The advisory client has executed a written consent prospectively authorizing the investment adviser, or any other person relying on this rule, to effect agency cross transactions for such advisory client, provided that such written consent is obtained after full written disclosure that with respect to agency cross transactions the investment adviser or such other person will act as broker for, receive commissions from, and have a potentially conflicting division of loyalties and responsibilities regarding, both parties to such transactions;</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Provided, however,</E>(2) The investment adviser, or any other person relying on this rule, sends to each such client a written confirmation at or before the completion of each such transaction, which confirmation includes (i) a statement of the nature of such transaction, (ii) the date such transaction took place, (iii) an offer to furnish upon request, the time when such transaction took place, and (iv) the source and amount of any other remuneration received or to be received by the investment adviser and any other person relying on this rule in connection with the transaction,That if, in the case of a purchase, neither the investment adviser nor any other person relying on this rule was participating in a distribution, or in the case of a sale, neither the investment adviser nor any other person relying on this rule was participating in a tender offer, the written confirmation may state whether any other remuneration has been or will be received and that the source and amount of such other remuneration will be furnished upon written request of such customer;</P>
            <P>(3) The investment adviser, or any other person relying in this rule, sends to each such client, at least annually, and with or as part of any written statement or summary of such account from the investment adviser or such other person, a written disclosure statement identifying the total number of such transactions during the period since the date of the last such statement or summary, and the total amount of all commissions or other remuneration received or to be received by the investment adviser or any other person relying on this rule in connection with such transactions during such period;</P>
            <P>(4) Each written disclosure statement and confirmation required by this rule includes a conspicuous statement that the written consent referred to in paragraph (a)(1) of this section may be revoked at any time by written notice to the investment adviser, or to any other person relying on this rule, from the advisory client; and</P>
            <P>(5) No such transaction is effected in which the same investment adviser or an investment adviser and any person controlling, controlled by or under common control with such investment adviser recommended the transaction to both any seller and any purchaser.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">agency cross transaction for an advisory client</E>(b) For purposes of this rule the termshall mean a transaction in which a person acts as an investment adviser in relation to a transaction in which such investment adviser, or any person controlling, controlled by, or under common control with such investment adviser, acts as broker for both such advisory client and for another person on the other side of the transaction.</P>

            <P>(c) This rule shall not be construed as relieving in any way the investment adviser or another person relying on this rule from acting in the best interests of the advisory client, including fulfilling the duty with respect to the best price and execution for the particular transaction for the advisory client; nor shall it relieve such person or persons from any disclosure obligation which may be imposed by subparagraphs (1) or (2) of section 206 of the<PRTPAGE P="972"/>Act or by other applicable provisions of the federal securities laws.</P>
            <CITA>[42 FR 29301 June 8, 1977, as amended at 48 FR 41379, Sept. 15, 1983; 62 FR 28135, May 22, 1997]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Advertisements by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) It shall constitute a fraudulent, deceptive, or manipulative act, practice, or course of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4)) for any investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), directly or indirectly, to publish, circulate, or distribute any advertisement:</P>
            <P>(1) Which refers, directly or indirectly, to any testimonial of any kind concerning the investment adviser or concerning any advice, anaylsis, report or other service rendered by such investment adviser; or</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Provided, however,</E>(2) Which refers, directly or indirectly, to past specific recommendations of such investment adviser which were or would have been profitable to any person:That this shall not prohibit an advertisement which sets out or offers to furnish a list of all recommendations made by such investment adviser within the immediately preceding period of not less than one year if such advertisement, and such list if it is furnished separately: (i) State the name of each such security recommended, the date and nature of each such recommendation (e.g., whether to buy, sell or hold), the market price at that time, the price at which the recommendation was to be acted upon, and the market price of each such security as of the most recent practicable date, and (ii) contain the following cautionary legend on the first page thereof in print or type as large as the largest print or type used in the body or text thereof: “it should not be assumed that recommendations made in the future will be profitable or will equal the performance of the securities in this list”; or</P>
            <P>(3) Which represents, directly or indirectly, that any graph, chart, formula or other device being offered can in and of itself be used to determine which securities to buy or sell, or when to buy or sell them; or which represents directly or indirectly, that any graph, chart, formula or other device being offered will assist any person in making his own decisions as to which securities to buy, sell, or when to buy or sell them, without prominently disclosing in such advertisement the limitations thereof and the difficulties with respect to its use; or</P>
            <P>(4) Which contains any statement to the effect that any report, analysis, or other service will be furnished free or without charge, unless such report, analysis or other service actually is or will be furnished entirely free and without any condition or obligation, directly or indirectly; or</P>
            <P>(5) Which contains any untrue statement of a material fact, or which is otherwise false or misleading.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">advertisement</E>(b) For the purposes of this section the termshall include any notice, circular, letter or other written communication addressed to more than one person, or any notice or other announcement in any publication or by radio or television, which offers (1) any analysis, report, or publication concerning securities, or which is to be used in making any determination as to when to buy or sell any security, or which security to buy or sell, or (2) any graph, chart, formula, or other device to be used in making any determination as to when to buy or sell any security, or which security to buy or sell, or (3) any other investment advisory service with regard to securities.</P>
            <SECAUTH>(Sec. 206, 54 Stat. 852, as amended; 15 U.S.C. 80b-6)</SECAUTH>
            <CITA>[26 FR 10549, Nov. 9, 1961, as amended at 62 FR 28135, May 22, 1997]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Custody of funds or securities of clients by investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Safekeeping required.</E>
                <E T="03">Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4))</E>If you are an investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), it is a fraudulent, deceptive, or manipulative act, practice or course of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of thefor you to have custody of client funds or securities unless:</P>
            <P>(1)<E T="03">Qualified custodian.</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="973"/>A qualified custodian maintains those funds and securities:</P>
            <P>(i) In a separate account for each client under that client's name; or</P>
            <P>(ii) In accounts that contain only your clients' funds and securities, under your name as agent or trustee for the clients.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Notice to clients.</E>If you open an account with a qualified custodian on your client's behalf, either under the client's name or under your name as agent, you notify the client in writing of the qualified custodian's name, address, and the manner in which the funds or securities are maintained, promptly when the account is opened and following any changes to this information. If you send account statements to a client to which you are required to provide this notice, include in the notification provided to that client and in any subsequent account statement you send that client a statement urging the client to compare the account statements from the custodian with those from the adviser.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Account statements to clients.</E>You have a reasonable basis, after due inquiry, for believing that the qualified custodian sends an account statement, at least quarterly, to each of your clients for which it maintains funds or securities, identifying the amount of funds and of each security in the account at the end of the period and setting forth all transactions in the account during that period.</P>
            <P>(4)<E T="03">Independent verification.</E>The client funds and securities of which you have custody are verified by actual examination at least once during each calendar year, except as provided below, by an independent public accountant, pursuant to a written agreement between you and the accountant, at a time that is chosen by the accountant without prior notice or announcement to you and that is irregular from year to year. The written agreement must provide for the first examination to occur within six months of becoming subject to this paragraph, except that, if you maintain client funds or securities pursuant to this section as a qualified custodian, the agreement must provide for the first examination to occur no later than six months after obtaining the internal control report. The written agreement must require the accountant to:</P>
            <P>(i) File a certificate on Form ADV-E (17 CFR 279.8) with the Commission within 120 days of the time chosen by the accountant in paragraph (a)(4) of this section, stating that it has examined the funds and securities and describing the nature and extent of the examination;</P>
            <P>(ii) Upon finding any material discrepancies during the course of the examination, notify the Commission within one business day of the finding, by means of a facsimile transmission or electronic mail, followed by first class mail, directed to the attention of the Director of the Office of Compliance Inspections and Examinations; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Upon resignation or dismissal from, or other termination of, the engagement, or upon removing itself or being removed from consideration for being reappointed, file within four business days Form ADV-E accompanied by a statement that includes:</P>
            <P>(A) The date of such resignation, dismissal, removal, or other termination, and the name, address, and contact information of the accountant; and</P>
            <P>(B) An explanation of any problems relating to examination scope or procedure that contributed to such resignation, dismissal, removal, or other termination.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Special rule for limited partnerships and limited liability companies.</E>(5)If you or a related person is a general partner of a limited partnership (or managing member of a limited liability company, or hold a comparable position for another type of pooled investment vehicle), the account statements required under paragraph (a)(3) of this section must be sent to each limited partner (or member or other beneficial owner).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Investment advisers acting as qualified custodians.</E>(6)If you maintain, or if you have custody because a related person maintains, client funds or securities pursuant to this section as a qualified custodian in connection with advisory services you provide to clients:</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="974"/>(i) The independent public accountant you retain to perform the independent verification required by paragraph (a)(4) of this section must be registered with, and subject to regular inspection as of the commencement ofthe professional engagement period, and as of each calendar year-end, by, the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board in accordance with its rules; and</P>
            <P>(ii) You must obtain, or receive from your related person, within six months of becoming subject to this paragraph and thereafter no less frequently than once each calendar year a written internal control report prepared by an independent public accountant:</P>
            <P>(A) The internal control report must include an opinion of an independent public accountant as to whether controls have been placed in operation as of a specific date, and are suitably designed and are operating effectively to meet control objectives relating to custodial services, including the safeguarding of funds and securities held by either you or a related person on behalf of your advisory clients, during the year;</P>
            <P>(B) The independent public accountant must verify that the funds and securities are reconciled to a custodian other than you or your related person; and</P>
            <P>(C) The independent public accountant must be registered with, and subject to regular inspection as of the commencement of the professional engagement period, and as of each calendar year-end, by, the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board in accordance with its rules.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Independent representatives.</E>(7)A client may designate an independent representative to receive, on his behalf, notices and account statements as required under paragraphs (a)(2) and (a)(3) of this section.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Exceptions.</E>
                <E T="03">Shares of mutual funds.</E>(1)With respect to shares of an open-end company as defined in section 5(a)(1) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-5(a)(1)) (“mutual fund”), you may use the mutual fund's transfer agent in lieu of a qualified custodian for purposes of complying with paragraph (a) of this section.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Certain privately offered securities.</E>(2)(i) You are not required to comply with paragraph (a)(1) of this section with respect to securities that are:</P>
            <P>(A) Acquired from the issuer in a transaction or chain of transactions not involving any public offering;</P>
            <P>(B) Uncertificated, and ownership thereof is recorded only on the books of the issuer or its transfer agent in the name of the client; and</P>
            <P>(C) Transferable only with prior consent of the issuer or holders of the outstanding securities of the issuer.</P>
            <P>(ii) Notwithstanding paragraph (b)(2)(i) of this section, the provisions of this paragraph (b)(2) are available with respect to securities held for the account of a limited partnership (or a limited liability company, or other type of pooled investment vehicle) only if the limited partnership is audited, and the audited financial statements are distributed, as described in paragraph (b)(4) of this section.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Fee deduction.</E>Notwithstanding paragraph (a)(4) of this section, you are not required to obtain an independent verification of client funds and securities maintained by a qualified custodian if:</P>
            <P>(i) you have custody of the funds and securities solely as a consequence of your authority to make withdrawals from client accounts to pay your advisory fee; and</P>
            <P>(ii) if the qualified custodian is a related person, you can rely on paragraph (b)(6) of this section.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Limited partnerships subject to annual audit.</E>(4)You are not required to comply with paragraphs (a)(2) and (a)(3) of this section and you shall be deemed to have complied with paragraph (a)(4) of this section with respect to the account of a limited partnership (or limited liability company, or another type of pooled investment vehicle) that is subject to audit (as defined in rule 1-02(d) of Regulation S-X (17 CFR 210.1-02(d))):</P>
            <P>(i) At least annually and distributes its audited financial statements prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles to all limited partners (or members or other beneficial owners) within 120 days of the end of its fiscal year;</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="975"/>(ii) By an independent public accountant that is registered with, and subject to regular inspection as of the commencement of the professional engagement period, and as of each calendar year-end, by, the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board in accordance with its rules; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Upon liquidation and distributes its audited financial statements prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles to all limited partners (or members or other beneficial owners) promptly after the completion of such audit.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Registered investment companies.</E>(5)You are not required to comply with this section (17 CFR 275.206(4)-2) with respect to the account of an investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-1 to 80a-64).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Certain Related Persons.</E>(6)Notwithstanding paragraph (a)(4) of this section, you are not required to obtain an independent verification of client funds and securities if:</P>
            <P>(i) you have custody under this rule solely because a related person holds, directly or indirectly, client funds or securities, or has any authority to obtain possession of them, in connection with advisory services you provide to clients; and</P>
            <P>(ii) your related person is operationally independent of you.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Delivery to Related Person.</E>(c)Sending an account statement under paragraph (a)(5) of this section or distributing audited financial statements under paragraph (b)(4) of this section shall not satisfy the requirements of this section if such account statements or financial statements are sent solely to limited partners (or members or other beneficial owners) that themselves are limited partnerships (or limited liability companies, or another type of pooled investment vehicle) and are your related persons.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Definitions.</E>(d)For the purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Control</E>(1)means the power, directly or indirectly, to direct the management or policies of a person, whether through ownership of securities, by contract, or otherwise. Control includes:</P>
            <P>(i) Each of your firm's officers, partners, or directors exercising executive responsibility (or persons having similar status or functions) is presumed to control your firm;</P>
            <P>(ii) A person is presumed to control a corporation if the person:</P>
            <P>(A) Directly or indirectly has the right to vote 25 percent or more of a class of the corporation's voting securities; or</P>
            <P>(B) Has the power to sell or direct the sale of 25 percent or more of a class of the corporation's voting securities;</P>
            <P>(iii) A person is presumed to control a partnership if the person has the right to receive upon dissolution, or has contributed, 25 percent or more of the capital of the partnership;</P>
            <P>(iv) A person is presumed to control a limited liability company if the person:</P>
            <P>(A) Directly or indirectly has the right to vote 25 percent or more of a class of the interests of the limited liability company;</P>
            <P>(B) Has the right to receive upon dissolution, or has contributed, 25 percent or more of the capital of the limited liability company; or</P>
            <P>(C) Is an elected manager of the limited liability company; or</P>
            <P>(v) A person is presumed to control a trust if the person is a trustee or managing agent of the trust.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Custody</E>(2)means holding, directly or indirectly, client funds or securities, or having any authority to obtain possession of them. You have custody if a related person holds, directly or indirectly, client funds or securities, or has any authority to obtain possession of them, in connection with advisory services you provide to clients. Custody includes:</P>
            <P>(i) Possession of client funds or securities (but not of checks drawn by clients and made payable to third parties) unless you receive them inadvertently and you return them to the sender promptly but in any case within three business days of receiving them;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any arrangement (including a general power of attorney) under which you are authorized or permitted to withdraw client funds or securities maintained with a custodian upon your instruction to the custodian; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Any capacity (such as general partner of a limited partnership, managing member of a limited liability company or a comparable position for another type of pooled investment vehicle, or trustee of a trust) that gives you or your supervised person legal ownership of or access to client funds or securities.</P>
            <P>(3)<E
                    T="03">Independent public accountant</E>means a public accountant that meets<PRTPAGE P="976"/>the standards of independence described in rule 2-01(b) and (c) of Regulation S-X (17 CFR 210.2-01(b) and (c)).</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Independent representative</E>(4)means a person that:</P>
            <P>(i) Acts as agent for an advisory client, including in the case of a pooled investment vehicle, for limited partners of a limited partnership (or members of a limited liability company, or other beneficial owners of another type of pooled investment vehicle) and by law or contract is obliged to act in the best interest of the advisory client or the limited partners (or members, or other beneficial owners);</P>
            <P>(ii) Does not control, is not controlled by, and is not under common control with you; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Does not have, and has not had within the past two years, a material business relationship with you.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Operationally independent:</E>(5)for purposes of paragraph (b)(6) of this section, a related person is presumed not to be operationally independent unless each of the following conditions is met and no other circumstances can reasonably be expected to compromise the operational independence of the related person: (i) Client assets in the custody of the related person are not subject to claims of the adviser's creditors; (ii) advisory personnel do not have custody or possession of, or direct or indirect access to client assets of which the related person has custody, or the power to control the disposition of such client assets to third parties for the benefit of the adviser or its related persons, or otherwise have the opportunity to misappropriate such client assets; (iii) advisory personnel and personnel of the related person who have access to advisory client assets are not under common supervision; and (iv) advisory personnel do not hold any position with the related person or share premises with the related person.</P>
            <P>(6)<E T="03">Qualified custodian</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) A bank as defined in section 202(a)(2) of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-2(a)(2)) or a savings association as defined in section 3(b)(1) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (12 U.S.C. 1813(b)(1)) that has deposits insured by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation under the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (12 U.S.C. 1811);</P>
            <P>(ii) A broker-dealer registered under section 15(b)(1) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78o(b)(1)), holding the client assets in customer accounts;</P>
            <P>(iii) A futures commission merchant registered under section 4f(a) of the Commodity Exchange Act (7 U.S.C. 6f(a)), holding the client assets in customer accounts, but only with respect to clients' funds and security futures, or other securities incidental to transactions in contracts for the purchase or sale of a commodity for future delivery and options thereon; and</P>
            <P>(iv) A foreign financial institution that customarily holds financial assets for its customers, provided that the foreign financial institution keeps the advisory clients' assets in customer accounts segregated from its proprietary assets.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Related person</E>(7)means any person, directly or indirectly, controlling or controlled by you, and any person that is under common control with you.</P>
            <CITA>[75 FR 1484, Jan. 11, 2010]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-3</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Cash payments for client solicitations.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) It shall be unlawful for any investment adviser required to be registered pursuant to section 203 of the Act to pay a cash fee, directly or indirectly, to a solicitor with respect to solicitation activities unless:</P>
            <P>(1)(i) The investment adviser is registered under the Act;</P>
            <P>(ii) The solicitor is not a person (A) subject to a Commission order issued under section 203(f) of the Act, or (B) convicted within the previous ten years of any felony or misdemeanor involving conduct described in section 203(e)(2)(A) through (D) of the Act, or (C) who has been found by the Commission to have engaged, or has been convicted of engaging, in any of the conduct specified in paragraphs (1), (5) or (6) of section 203(e) of the Act, or (D) is subject to an order, judgment or decree described in section 203(e)(4) of the Act; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Such cash fee is paid pursuant to a written agreement to which the adviser is a party; and</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
                <P>
                    <PRTPAGE P="977"/>The investment adviser shall retain a copy of each written agreement requiredby this paragraph as part of the records required to be kept under § 275.204-2(a)(10) of this chapter.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(2) Such cash fee is paid to a solicitor:</P>
            <P>(i) With respect to solicitation activities for the provision of impersonal advisory services only; or</P>

            <P>(ii) Who is (A) a partner, officer, director or employee of such investment adviser or (B) a partner, officer, director or employee of a person which controls, is controlled by, or is under common control with such investment adviser:<E T="03">Provided,</E>That the status of such solicitor as a partner, officer, director or employee of such investment adviser or other person, and any affiliation between the investment adviser and such other person, is disclosed to the client at the time of the solicitation or referral; or</P>
            <P>(iii) Other than a solicitor specified in paragraph (a)(2) (i) or (ii) of this section if all of the following conditions are met:</P>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">1</E>(A) The written agreement required by paragraph (a)(1)(iii) of this section: (<E
                    T="03">2</E>) Describes the solicitation activities to be engaged in by the solicitor on behalf of the investment adviser and the compensation to be received therefor; () contains an undertaking by the solicitor to perform his duties under the agreement in a manner consistent with the instructions of the investment adviser and the provisions of the Act and the rules thereunder; (<E T="03">3</E>) requires that the solicitor, at the time of any solicitation activities for which compensation is paid or to be paid by the investment adviser, provide the client with a current copy of the investment adviser's written disclosure statement required by § 275.204-3 of this chapter (“brochure rule”) and a separate written disclosure document described in paragraph (b) of this rule.</P>
            <P>(B) The investment adviser receives from the client, prior to, or at the time of, entering into any written or oral investment advisory contract with such client, a signed and dated acknowledgment of receipt of the investment adviser's written disclosure statement and the solicitor's written disclosure document.</P>
            <NOTE>
                <HD SOURCE="HED">Note:</HD>
                <P>The investment adviser shall retain a copy of each such acknowledgment and solicitor disclosure document as part of the records required to be kept under § 275.204-2(a)(15) of this chapter.</P>
            </NOTE>
            <P>(C) The investment adviser makes a bona fide effort to ascertain whether the solicitor has complied with the agreement, and has a reasonable basis for believing that the solicitor has so complied.</P>
            <P>(b) The separate written disclosure document required to be furnished by the solicitor to the client pursuant to this section shall contain the following information:</P>
            <P>(1) The name of the solicitor;</P>
            <P>(2) The name of the investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(3) The nature of the relationship, including any affiliation, between the solicitor and the investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(4) A statement that the solicitor will be compensated for his solicitation services by the investment adviser;</P>
            <P>(5) The terms of such compensation arrangement, including a description of the compensation paid or to be paid to the solicitor; and</P>
            <P>(6) The amount, if any, for the cost of obtaining his account the client will be charged in addition to the advisory fee, and the differential, if any, among clients with respect to the amount or level of advisory fees charged by the investment adviser if such differential is attributable to the existence of any arrangement pursuant to which the investment adviser has agreed to compensate the solicitor for soliciting clients for, or referring clients to, the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(c) Nothing in this section shall be deemed to relieve any person of any fiduciary or other obligation to which such person may be subject under any law.</P>
            <P>(d) For purposes of this section,</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Solicitor</E>(1)means any person who, directly or indirectly, solicits any client for, or refers any client to, an investment adviser.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Client</E>(2)includes any prospective client.</P>
            <P>(3)<E T="03">Impersonal advisory services</E>
                <PRTPAGE P="978"/>means investment advisory services provided solely by means of (i) written materials or oral statements which do not purport to meet the objectives or needs of the specific client, (ii) statistical information containing no expressions ofopinions as to the investment merits of particular securities, or (iii) any combination of the foregoing services.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Special rule for solicitation of government entity clients.</E>(e)Solicitation activities involving a government entity, as defined in § 275.206(4)-5, shall be subject to the additional limitations set forth in that section.</P>
            <CITA>[44 FR 42130, July 18, 1979; 54 FR 32441, Aug. 8, 1989, as amended at 62 FR 28135, May 22, 1997; 63 FR 39716, July 24, 1998; 75 FR 41069, July 14, 2010]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-4</SECTNO>
            <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-5</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Political contributions by certain investment advisers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Prohibitions.</E>(a)As a means reasonably designed to prevent fraudulent, deceptive or manipulative acts, practices, or courses of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4)), it shall be unlawful:</P>
            <P>(1) For any investment adviser registered (or required to be registered) with the Commission, or unregistered in reliance on the exemption available under section 203(b)(3) of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)), or that is an exempt reporting adviser, as defined in section 275.204-4(a), to provide investment advisory services for compensation to a government entity within two years after a contribution to an official of the government entity is made by the investment adviser or any covered associate of the investment adviser (including a person who becomes a covered associate within two years after the contribution is made); and</P>
            <P>(2) For any investment adviser registered (or required to be registered) with the Commission, or unregistered in reliance on the exemption available under section 203(b)(3) of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)), or that is an exempt reporting adviser, or any of the investment adviser's covered associates:</P>
            <P>(i) To provide or agree to provide, directly or indirectly, payment to any person to solicit a government entity for investment advisory services on behalf of such investment adviser unless such person is:</P>
            <P>(A) A regulated person; or</P>
            <P>(B) An executive officer, general partner, managing member (or, in each case, a person with a similar status or function), or employee of the investment adviser; and</P>
            <P>(ii) To coordinate, or to solicit any person or political action committee to make, any:</P>
            <P>(A) Contribution to an official of a government entity to which the investment adviser is providing or seeking to provide investment advisory services; or</P>
            <P>(B) Payment to a political party of a State or locality where the investment adviser is providing or seeking to provide investment advisory services to a government entity.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Exceptions</E>—(1)<E T="03">De minimis exception.</E>
                <E
                    T="03">was</E>Paragraph (a)(1) of this section does not apply to contributions made by a covered associate, if a natural person, to officials for whom the covered associateentitled to vote at the time of the contributions and which in the aggregate do not exceed $350 to any one official, per election, or to officials for whom the covered associate was not<E T="03"/>entitled to vote at the time of the contributions and which in the aggregate do not exceed $150 to any one official, per election.</P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Exception for certain new covered associates.</E>The prohibitions of paragraph (a)(1) of this section shall not apply to an investment adviser as a result of a contribution made by a natural person more than six months prior to becoming a covered associate of the investment adviser unless such person, after becoming a covered associate, solicits clients on behalf of the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Exception for certain returned contributions.</E>(3)(i) An investment adviser that is prohibited from providing investment advisory services for compensation pursuant to paragraph (a)(1) of this section as a result of a contribution made by a covered associate of the investment adviser is excepted from such prohibition, subject to paragraphs (b)(3)(ii) and (b)(3)(iii) of this section, upon satisfaction of the following requirements:</P>

            <P>(A) The investment adviser must have discovered the contribution which resulted in the prohibition within four months of the date of such contribution;<PRTPAGE P="979"/>
            </P>
            <P>(B) Such contribution must not have exceeded $350; and</P>
            <P>(C) The contributor must obtain a return of the contribution within 60 calendar days of the date of discovery of such contribution by the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(ii) In any calendar year, an investment adviser that has reported on its annual updating amendment to Form ADV (17 CFR 279.1) that it has more than 50 employees is entitled to no more than three exceptions pursuant to paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section, and an investment adviser that has reported on its annual updating amendment to Form ADV that it has 50 or fewer employees is entitled to no more than two exceptions pursuant to paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section.</P>
            <P>(iii) An investment adviser may not rely on the exception provided in paragraph (b)(3)(i) of this section more than once with respect to contributions by the same covered associate of the investment adviser regardless of the time period.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Prohibitions as applied to covered investment pools.</E>(c)For purposes of this section, an investment adviser to a covered investment pool in which a government entity invests or is solicited to invest shall be treated as though that investment adviser were providing or seeking to provide investment advisory services directly to the government entity.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Further prohibition.</E>(d)As a means reasonably designed to prevent fraudulent, deceptive or manipulative acts, practices, or courses of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4)), it shall be unlawful for any investment adviser registered (or required to be registered) with the Commission, or unregistered in reliance on the exemption available under section 203(b)(3) of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3(b)(3)), or that is an exempt reporting adviser, or any of the investment adviser's covered associates to do anything indirectly which, if done directly, would result in a violation of this section.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Exemptions.</E>(e)The Commission, upon application, may conditionally or unconditionally exempt an investment adviser from the prohibition under paragraph (a)(1) of this section. In determining whether to grant an exemption, the Commission will consider, among other factors:</P>
            <P>(1) Whether the exemption is necessary or appropriate in the public interest and consistent with the protection of investors and the purposes fairly intended by the policy and provisions of the Advisers Act (15 U.S.C. 80b);</P>
            <P>(2) Whether the investment adviser:</P>
            <P>(i) Before the contribution resulting in the prohibition was made, adopted and implemented policies and procedures reasonably designed to prevent violations of this section; and</P>
            <P>(ii) Prior to or at the time the contribution which resulted in such prohibition was made, had no actual knowledge of the contribution; and</P>
            <P>(iii) After learning of the contribution:</P>
            <P>(A) Has taken all available steps to cause the contributor involved in making the contribution which resulted in such prohibition to obtain a return of the contribution; and</P>
            <P>(B) Has taken such other remedial or preventive measures as may be appropriate under the circumstances;</P>
            <P>(3) Whether, at the time of the contribution, the contributor was a covered associate or otherwise an employee of the investment adviser, or was seeking such employment;</P>
            <P>(4) The timing and amount of the contribution which resulted in the prohibition;</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">e.g,</E>(5) The nature of the election (Federal, State or local); and</P>
            <P>(6) The contributor's apparent intent or motive in making the contribution which resulted in the prohibition, as evidenced by the facts and circumstances surrounding such contribution.</P>
            <P>(f)<E T="03">Definitions.</E>For purposes of this section:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Contribution</E>(1)means any gift, subscription, loan, advance, or deposit of money or anything of value made for:</P>
            <P>(i) The purpose of influencing any election for Federal, State or local office;</P>
            <P>(ii) Payment of debt incurred in connection with any such election; or</P>

            <P>(iii) Transition or inaugural expenses of the successful candidate for State or local office.<PRTPAGE P="980"/>
            </P>
            <P>(2)<E T="03">Covered associate</E>of an investment adviser means:</P>
            <P>(i) Any general partner, managing member or executive officer, or other person with a similar status or function;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any employee who solicits a government entity for the investment adviser and any person who supervises, directly or indirectly, such employee; and</P>
            <P>(iii) Any political action committee controlled by the investment adviser or by any person described in paragraphs (f)(2)(i) and (f)(2)(ii) of this section.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Covered investment pool</E>(3)means:</P>
            <P>(i) An investment company registered under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a) that is an investment option of a plan or program of a government entity; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Any company that would be an investment company under section 3(a) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(a)), but for the exclusion provided from that definition by either section 3(c)(1), section 3(c)(7) or section 3(c)(11) of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(1), (c)(7) or (c)(11)).</P>
            <P>(4)<E T="03">Executive officer</E>of an investment adviser means:</P>
            <P>(i) The president;</P>
            <P>(ii) Any vice president in charge of a principal business unit, division or function (such as sales, administration or finance);</P>
            <P>(iii) Any other officer of the investment adviser who performs a policy-making function; or</P>
            <P>(iv) Any other person who performs similar policy-making functions for the investment adviser.</P>
            <P>(5)<E T="03">Government entity</E>means any State or political subdivision of a State, including:</P>
            <P>(i) Any agency, authority, or instrumentality of the State or political subdivision;</P>
            <P>(ii) A pool of assets sponsored or established by the State or political subdivision or any agency, authority or instrumentality thereof, including, but not limited to a “defined benefit plan” as defined in section 414(j) of the Internal Revenue Code (26 U.S.C. 414(j)), or a State general fund;</P>
            <P>(iii) A plan or program of a government entity; and</P>
            <P>(iv) Officers, agents, or employees of the State or political subdivision or any agency, authority or instrumentality thereof, acting in their official capacity.</P>
            <P>(6)<E T="03">Official</E>means any person (including any election committee for the person) who was, at the time of the contribution, an incumbent, candidate or successful candidate for elective office of a government entity, if the office:</P>
            <P>(i) Is directly or indirectly responsible for, or can influence the outcome of, the hiring of an investment adviser by a government entity; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Has authority to appoint any person who is directly or indirectly responsible for, or can influence the outcome of, the hiring of an investment adviser by a government entity.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Payment</E>(7)means any gift, subscription, loan, advance, or deposit of money or anything of value.</P>
            <P>(8)<E T="03">Plan or program of a government entity</E>means any participant-directed investment program or plan sponsored or established by a State or political subdivision or any agency, authority or instrumentality thereof, including, but not limited to, a “qualified tuition plan” authorized by section 529 of the Internal Revenue Code (26 U.S.C. 529), a retirement plan authorized by section 403(b) or 457 of the Internal Revenue Code (26 U.S.C. 403(b) or 457), or any similar program or plan.</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Regulated person</E>(9)means:</P>
            <P>(i) An investment adviser registered with the Commission that has not, and whose covered associates have not, within two years of soliciting a government entity:</P>
            <P>(A) Made a contribution to an official of that government entity, other than as described in paragraph (b)(1) of this section; and</P>
            <P>(B) Coordinated or solicited any person or political action committee to make any contribution or payment described in paragraphs (a)(2)(ii)(A) and (B) of this section;</P>
            <P>
                <PRTPAGE P="981"/>(ii) A “broker,” as defined in section 3(a)(4) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(4)) or a “dealer,” as defined in section 3(a)(5) of that Act (15 U.S.C. 78c(a)(5)), that is registered with the Commission, and is amember of a national securities association registered under 15A of that Act (15 U.S.C. 78o-3), provided that:</P>
            <P>(A) The rules of the association prohibit members from engaging in distribution or solicitation activities if certain political contributions have been made; and</P>
            <P>(B) The Commission, by order, finds that such rules impose substantially equivalent or more stringent restrictions on broker-dealers than this section imposes on investment advisers and that such rules are consistent with the objectives of this section; and</P>
            <P>(iii) A “municipal advisor” registered with the Commission under section 15B of the Exchange Act and subject to rules of the Municipal Securities Rulemaking Board, provided that:</P>
            <P>(A) Such rules prohibit municipal advisors from engaging in distribution or solicitation activities if certain political contributions have been made; and</P>
            <P>(B) The Commission, by order, finds that such rules impose substantially equivalent or more stringent restrictions on municipal advisors than this section imposes on investment advisers and that such rules are consistent with the objectives of this section.</P>
            <P>(10)<E T="03">Solicit</E>means:</P>
            <P>(i) With respect to investment advisory services, to communicate, directly or indirectly, for the purpose of obtaining or retaining a client for, or referring a client to, an investment adviser; and</P>
            <P>(ii) With respect to a contribution or payment, to communicate, directly or indirectly, for the purpose of obtaining or arranging a contribution or payment.</P>
            <CITA>[75 FR 41069, July 14, 2010, as amended at 76 FR 43013, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-6</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Proxy voting.</SUBJECT>
            <P>If you are an investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), it is a fraudulent, deceptive, or manipulative act, practice or course of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4)), for you to exercise voting authority with respect to client securities, unless you:</P>
            <P>(a) Adopt and implement written policies and procedures that are reasonably designed to ensure that you vote client securities in the best interest of clients, which procedures must include how you address material conflicts that may arise between your interests and those of your clients;</P>
            <P>(b) Disclose to clients how they may obtain information from you about how you voted with respect to their securities; and</P>
            <P>(c) Describe to clients your proxy voting policies and procedures and, upon request, furnish a copy of the policies and procedures to the requesting client.</P>
            <CITA>[68 FR 6593, Feb. 7, 2003]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-7</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Compliance procedures and practices.</SUBJECT>
            <P>If you are an investment adviser registered or required to be registered under section 203 of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80b-3), it shall be unlawful within the meaning of section 206 of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6) for you to provide investment advice to clients unless you:</P>
            <P>(a)<E T="03">Policies and procedures.</E>Adopt and implement written policies and procedures reasonably designed to prevent violation, by you and your supervised persons, of the Act and the rules that the Commission has adopted under the Act;</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Annual review.</E>(b)Review, no less frequently than annually, the adequacy of the policies and procedures established pursuant to this section and the effectiveness of their implementation; and</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Chief compliance officer.</E>(c)Designate an individual (who is a supervised person) responsible for administering the policies and procedures that you adopt under paragraph (a) of this section.</P>
            <CITA>[68 FR 74730, Dec. 24, 2003]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.206(4)-8</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Pooled investment vehicles.</SUBJECT>
            <P>
                <E
                    T="03">Prohibition.</E>(a)It shall constitute a fraudulent, deceptive, or manipulative act, practice, or course of business within the meaning of section 206(4) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-6(4)) for any investment adviser to a pooled investment vehicle to:<PRTPAGE P="982"/>
            </P>
            <P>(1) Make any untrue statement of a material fact or to omit to state a material fact necessary to make the statements made, in the light of the circumstances under which they were made, not misleading, to any investor or prospective investor in the pooled investment vehicle; or</P>
            <P>(2) Otherwise engage in any act, practice, or course of business that is fraudulent, deceptive, or manipulative with respect to any investor or prospective investor in the pooled investment vehicle.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Definition.</E>For purposes of this section “pooled investment vehicle” means any investment company as defined in section 3(a) of the Investment Company Act of 1940 (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(a)) or any company that would be an investment company under section 3(a) of that Act but for the exclusion provided from that definition by either section 3(c)(1) or section 3(c)(7) of that Act (15 U.S.C. 80a-3(c)(1) or (7)).</P>
            <CITA>[72 FR 44761, Aug. 9, 2007]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.222-1</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
            <P>For purposes of section 222 (15 U.S.C. 80b-18a) of the Act:</P>
            <P>
                <E T="03">Place of business.</E>(a)“Place of business” of an investment adviser means:</P>
            <P>(1) An office at which the investment adviser regularly provides investment advisory services, solicits, meets with, or otherwise communicates with clients; and</P>
            <P>(2) Any other location that is held out to the general public as a location at which the investment adviser provides investment advisory services, solicits, meets with, or otherwise communicates with clients.</P>
            <P>(b)<E T="03">Principal office and place of business.</E>“Principal office and place of business” of an investment adviser means the executive office of the investment adviser from which the officers, partners, or managers of the investment adviser direct, control, and coordinate the activities of the investment adviser.</P>
            <CITA>[62 FR 28135, May 22, 1997, as amended at 76 FR 43014, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 275.222-2</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Definition of “client” for purposes of the national de minimis standard.</SUBJECT>
            <P>For purposes of section 222(d)(2) of the Act (15 U.S.C. 80b-18a(d)(2)), an investment adviser may rely upon the definition of “client” provided by § 275.202(a)(30)-1, without giving regard to paragraph (b)(4) of that section.</P>
            <CITA>[76 FR 43014, July 19, 2011]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
    </PART>
</CFRGRANULE>
